<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Neural Networks</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0893-6080(03)00026-1</article-id>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Some neural network applications in environmental sciences. Part II: advancing computational efficiency of environmental numerical models</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Vladimir M. Krasnopolsky</string-name>
          <email>vladimir.krasnopolsky@noaa.gov</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Fre´de´ric Chevallier</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>European Centre for Medium-Range Weather Forecasts</institution>
          ,
          <addr-line>Reading</addr-line>
          ,
          <country country="UK">UK</country>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <label>1</label>
          <institution>Science Applications International Corporation at National Centers for Environmental Prediction</institution>
          ,
          <addr-line>5200 Auth Road, Camp Spring, MD 20746</addr-line>
          ,
          <country country="US">USA</country>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>2003</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>16</volume>
      <issue>2003</issue>
      <fpage>335</fpage>
      <lpage>348</lpage>
      <abstract>
        <p>A new generic neural network (NN) application-improving computational efficiency of certain processes in numerical environmental models-is considered. This approach can be used to accelerate the calculations and improve the accuracy of the parameterizations of several types of physical processes which generally require computations involving complex mathematical expressions, including differential and integral equations, rules, restrictions and highly nonlinear empirical relations based on physical or statistical models. It is shown that, from a mathematical point of view, such parameterizations can usually be considered as continuous mappings (continuous dependencies between two vectors) and, therefore, NNs can be used to replace primary parameterization algorithms. In addition to fast and accurate approximation of the primary parameterization, NN also provides the entire Jacobian for very little computation cost. Four particular real-life applications of the NN approach are presented here: for oceanic numerical models, a NN approximation of the UNESCO equation of state of the sea water (NN for the density of the seawater) and an inversion of this equation (NN for the salinity of the seawater); for atmospheric numerical models, a NN approximation for long wave radiative transfer code; and for wave models, a NN approximation for the nonlinear wave - wave interaction. In all considered applications a significant acceleration of numerical computations has been achieved. The first two of these NN applications have already been implemented in the multi-scale ocean forecast system at NCEP. The NN approach introduced in this paper can provide numerically efficient solutions to a wide range of problems in numerical models where lengthy, complicated calculations, which describe physical, chemical and/or biological processes, must be repeated frequently. q 2003 Elsevier Science Ltd. All rights reserved.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Neural networks</kwd>
        <kwd>Numerical modeling</kwd>
        <kwd>Atmospheric modeling</kwd>
        <kwd>Oceanic modeling</kwd>
        <kwd>Wave modeling</kwd>
        <kwd>Equation of state</kwd>
        <kwd>Nonlinear interaction</kwd>
        <kwd>Parameterization of physics</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>www.elsevier.com/locate/neunet</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>In this paper, we discuss a recently emerged application
of neural networks (NNs) for efficient (fast and accurate)
calculations of the computationally expensive and complex
mathematical formulations involved in environmental
numerical models. Any atmospheric or oceanic circulation
model is based on a set of prognostic and diagnostic
differential equations together with additional equations
required to obtain a mathematically closed system. Such a
system, in principle, can then be solved to predict the
evolution of the environment in time if the initial conditions
and any required external boundary conditions are
prescribed. Even though the forecast problem may now be
considered solvable in a theoretical sense, in the real world
of simulation, it is necessary to deal with practical aspects of
available computational resources and minimize the
computer time taken to produce a run, in particular in the context
of operational forecast systems.</p>
      <p>
        The numerical model contains terms that appear in the
dynamical equations, representing the effects of
unresolvable subgrid scale processes. These effects need to be
parameterized in terms of the dependent variables. Also,
implicitly contained in the system are processes that deal
with model physics such as radiation, convection, nonlinear
wave – wave interaction, etc. which need to be
parameterized. Accurate treatments of such parameterizations
generally require computations involving complex mathematical
expressions, which may include differential and integral
equations, rules, restrictions, highly nonlinear empirical
expressions, etc. that are developed based on physical or
statistical models. The complex mathematical formulations
of these processes require considerable computational
resource.
For example, a spectral atmospheric model with a
welldeveloped description of physics and subgrid scale
parameterizations may spend up to 70% of calculation time for
simulating these processes
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">(Estrade, Tre´molet, &amp; Sela,
2001)</xref>
        . The infrared radiative heating/cooling code requires
more than 10% of the computing time in the European
Centre for Medium-Range Weather Forecast (ECMWF)
general circulation model and in the National Centers for
Environmental Prediction (NCEP) global model, even
though the computations are not afforded at every grid
point (at ECMWF) and at every time step.
      </p>
      <p>
        In ocean models, the estimation of the full UNESCO
equation of state to compute the seawater density,
represented by an empirically derived highly nonlinear
equation relating density to pressure, salinity, and
temperature, takes a very significant amount (, 40% in high
resolution models) of the total computational effort. In
addition, most forecast models include data assimilation
procedures as an integral part of the forecast system to
improve the initial conditions of the model. When dealing
with ocean models, most often the data assimilation consists
of assimilating surface and subsurface temperature
observations to correct the model’s thermal field. This
temperature correction automatically makes it necessary to adjust
the salinity field in the ocean model in order to avoid
gravitational instabilities in the water column. This requires
inverting the complicated oceanic equation of state, which
makes the computational effort even more time-consuming
than the forward problem of computing the density itself.
Another example where intensive computations are needed
in a forecast model is the calculation of the land surface
temperature using a set of equations describing the
atmospheric boundary layer and physical processes in the
soil. Yet another example of intensive computational
problem in forecast models is the wind wave forecasting
problem in which an exact calculation of the nonlinear
wave – wave interactions using the formulation of
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">Hasselmann (1963)</xref>
        takes a prohibitively long time.
      </p>
      <p>
        In view of the constraints imposed on the available
computer resources, the calculation time allowed for each
parameterization is strictly limited in most operational
forecast models. Hence, very often it is necessary to use
simplified forms of these complex representations in
carrying out the time integrations in a forecast model,
thereby sacrificing the accuracy of forecasts. For example,
the nonlinear wave interactions in a wave forecast model are
replaced by a simplified discrete interaction approximation
(DIA)
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24 ref26">(Hasselmann et al., 1985)</xref>
        . Similarly, simplified fast
parameterizations of physics are used in many parts of
atmospheric and oceanic models. In most of these cases,
accurate physical models have been developed, but they
cannot be used because they are computationally too
expensive. Often simplified (even oversimplified due to
computational efficiency requirements) parameterizations
are obtained, for example, by neglecting higher order terms
of perturbation theory, by using empirical approximations,
or simply by neglecting the effects, which complicate the
calculations. It is common in many parameterization
schemes that the number of input and output variables is
relatively small, whereas the volume of internal calculations
is large. A typical example is the parameterization of the
radiative fluxes in the atmosphere. Indeed, accurate
treatment of cloud- and aerosol-radiation interactions
involves elaborate and numerically onerous 3D scattering
methods. Hence, most often the specific parameterization is
a result of a compromise between accuracy and
computational efficiency with an (sometimes) unpredictable effect
on the forecast.
      </p>
      <p>Improvements in forecast modeling can be achieved not
only by improving the representation of such
parameterizations as our understanding of the underlying physical
processes increases but also by improving our ability to
compute these parameterizations accurately within the
constraints imposed by the available computer resources.</p>
      <p>In this paper we present some of the problems dealing
with physical parameterizations and their computations
from a different (formal mathematical) point of view,
namely that of improving the computational efficiency of
available algorithms. We propose a generic approach, which
is based on developing fast and accurate parameterizations
of physics by approximating solutions of exact physical
models using NNs. From this formal point of view an exact
(best known) physical model representing a physical
process performs a smooth conversion of an input vector
of parameters, X ¼ {x1; x2; …; xn}; X [ Rn into an output
vector of parameters, Y ¼ {y1; y2; …; ym}; Y [ Rm: Thus,
each output parameter yi is a continuous function of
multiple input variables x1; x2; …; xn (input vector X).
Symbolically this input – output dependence is depicted in
Fig. 1.a and can be written as
Y ¼ FðXÞ;</p>
      <p>X [ Rn; Y [ Rm
If X and Y are related through a cause and effect principle,
the forward parameterization, Eq. (1a), can be derived from
first principles. It is usually a well-posed problem. If the
inverse dependence
X ¼ f ðYÞ;</p>
      <p>
        X [ Rn; Y [ Rm
ð1aÞ
ð1bÞ
is required (Fig. 1b) in a numerical model, the inverse
problem should be solved, which implies that Eq. (1a)
should be inverted. A solution of the inverse problem (1b) or
an inverse parameterization provides each output parameter
xi as a continuous function of multiple input variables
y1; y2; …; ym (vector Y is an input vector now). Often the
inverse parameterization (1b) is an ill-posed problem, and
sometimes multiple values of X can correspond to a single
Y : Forward, Eq. (1a), and inverse, Eq. (1b),
parameterizations represent the same mathematical object—a continuous
mapping which is a continuous relationship between two
vectors. Usually these input/output relationships are highly
complex and nonlinear, but continuous or almost continuous
(with a finite number of finite discontinuities), for physical
processes taken into account in atmospheric, oceanic, and
wave models. Hence, if exact solutions to these complex
relationships are calculated, however expensive the
computational efforts may be, these solutions can be used by the
generic mathematical tool—that is, the NNs—to produce
fast and accurate approximations for continuous and almost
continuous mappings
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16 ref21 ref4 ref7 ref8">(Attali &amp; Page`s, 1997; Chen &amp; Chen
1995a,b; Cybenko, 1989; Funahashi, 1989)</xref>
        . In this
approach, the costly exact calculation of the physics needs
to be performed only once and ‘off line’ to enable the
development of the fast and accurate approximation. After
that only this fast and accurate approximation will be used
to calculate the physics (coefficients of differential
equations) ‘on line’ in a numerical model.
      </p>
      <p>We assume that the readers of this journal are well
familiar with the NN technique. Therefore we do not
describe this technique in the paper. We only present here a
brief list of main properties of NNs, which make them a very
suitable generic tool for our application.
† NNs are able to accurately approximate complicated
nonlinear input/output relationships (any continuous and
almost continuous nonlinear mappings).
† While training the NN is often time consuming, its
application is not. After the training is finished (it is
usually performed only once), each application of the
trained NN is an estimation of a simple algebraic
expression with known coefficients, which is practically
instantaneous (several tens of floating point additions and
multiplications).
† NNs are analytically differentiable, in a way that make
the calculation of entire Jacobian matrix cheap.
† NN technique is flexible enough to accommodate
various additional constraints, which may arise in this
application.</p>
      <p>In Section 2 of this paper we present two (forward and
inverse) parameterizations for oceanic models, in Section 3
for atmospheric, and in Section 4 a parameterization for
wind wave models developed using NNs. In Section 5, we
discuss some important features of our approach and some
generalizations of standard NN techniques, which are
required to accommodate these features.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>2. Oceanic applications: NNs for efficient calculation</title>
      <p>of sea water density or salinity from the UNESCO</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-4">
      <title>Equation of State</title>
      <p>
        In this section, we apply a NN technique to two related
problems in the fast calculation of physics in oceanic
modeling and data assimilation. (i) In most ocean models,
the UNESCO International Equation of State for Seawater
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">(UNESCO, 1981)</xref>
        (UES) is used for the calculation of the
seawater density at each point of a 3D grid using a relatively
small time step. The frequency of updating the density
depends on specifics of the model. For high-resolution
models, the solution of this equation consumes a significant
part of the overall computation time. (ii) In the data
assimilation process, assimilation of temperature alone,
without making corresponding adjustments to salinity, in
ocean models, which employ the full equation of state, can
lead to problems of gravitational instabilities
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48 ref5">(Chalikov et al.
1998; Woodgate, 1998)</xref>
        . To adjust the salinity, we need to
dr ðT ; S; PÞ ¼ rðT ; S; PÞ 2 1000
rðT ; S; PÞ ¼
calculate the salinity from UES as a function of temperature,
density and depth (or pressure), i.e. solve an inverse
problem in many points. Numerical inversion of the UES
is an iterative procedure, which can consume several orders
of magnitude more time than solving of the UES itself.
      </p>
      <p>
        The UES for seawater gives the following expression for
the density anomaly dr (kg/m3) as described by
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">Fofonoff
and Millard (1983)</xref>
        where r is the density of seawater in kg/m3, T the
temperature in 8C, S the salinity in practical salinity units
(psu), P the pressure, and KðT ; S; PÞ is a bulk modulus
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">(UNESCO, 1981)</xref>
        .
      </p>
      <p>The UES (2) is empirically based and given over a 3D
domain D ¼ { 2 2 , T , 40 8C, 0 , S , 40 psu, and
0 , P , 10; 000 decibars}. This domain represents all
possible combinations of T ; S; and P; which are globally
encountered. Mathematically, the functions rðT ; S; 0Þ and
KðT ; S; PÞ are represented by multi-dimensional high degree
polynomials and, as a result, the density (2) is a ratio of two
3D polynomials which contain more than 40 parameters.</p>
      <p>The UES has two major drawbacks when it is applied in
the context of ocean modeling. The first is its cumbersome
form. For high-resolution models, the solution of this
equation at each point of a 3D grid for each time step
consumes a significant part (up to 40%) of the overall
computation time. Second, it is not a simple matter using the
UES to obtain solutions for salinity of seawater, since this
solution represents an inverse dependence.</p>
      <p>
        The UES determines the density field from observed
temperature, salinity, and pressure to within a standard error
of approximately 0.009 kg m23; however, there are several
natural processes (e.g. variations in the composition of
dissolved salts)
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">(Apel, 1987)</xref>
        , contributing to the uncertainty
in the density of natural seawater. The resulting natural
uncertainty in the density is of the order of 0.1 kg m23
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31 ref33 ref45">(Krasnopolsky et al., 2000; Krasnopolsky, Chalikov, &amp;
Tolman, 2003)</xref>
        . Taking these uncertainties into account, it
does not make sense to use parameterization with higher
accuracy in numerical ocean models if accuracy and
computing time increase together. This is why the accuracy
of 0.1 kg m23 was selected as the expected accuracy for the
NN parameterization. The accuracy of the NN
parameterization for salinity expressed in terms of density was also
expected to be better than 0.1 kg m23.
      </p>
      <p>
        Since the depth Z is used in NCEP ocean model as a
vertical coordinate, and there exist a simple pressure – depth
relationship
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">(Krasnopolsky et al., 2003)</xref>
        , we use Z instead of
P in our consideration. The UES defines two relationships
(second relationship for salinity through inversion)
r ¼ rðT ; S; ZÞ
S ¼ SðT ; r; ZÞ
which are continuous mappings (degenerated mappings
because 1D vectors are on the left). The NN technique was
applied to approximate Eqs. (3a) and (3b). To create a
training set for these NNs parameterizations in the 3D
domain D (see earlier), 4000 points ðTi; Si; ZiÞ were
generated on a grid. The UES was used to estimate the
density of seawater, ri; for each point. This simulated data
set {ri; Ti; Si; Zi} was used in order to train the NNs to
extract density and salinity. NNs with three nonlinear
neurons in one hidden layer and one linear neuron in the
output layers were selected. Two NN parameterizations
were obtained (Fig. 2)
r ¼ rNNðT ; S; ZÞ
S ¼ SNNðT ; r; ZÞ
where both rNN and SNN are expressed by
rðSÞNN ¼
k "
X vrjðSÞ tanh
j¼1
n
X Vjið Þxi þ BrjðSÞ
      </p>
      <p>r S
i¼1
!#
where v; V; b; and B are NN weights and biases.
Derivatives (Jacobian matrix) shown in Fig. 2 as additional
NN outputs are not actual outputs, which are trained during
the NN training; they are calculated analytically through
direct differentiating Eq. (5). The NN parameterization (4a)
for the density is about two times faster then the UES. The
calculation of the Jacobian matrix with the NN
parameterization requires an additional time, which is about 70% of
time required for the calculation of density. The NN
parameterization (4b) for the salinity is several hundreds
ð3bÞ
ð4aÞ
ð4bÞ
þ brðSÞ
ð5Þ
ð3aÞ</p>
      <p>Fig. 2. Schematic representation of NN parameterizations for the density
and salinity of seawater. Additional outputs for derivatives are not trained,
they are calculated.
times faster than an iterative numerical inversion of the
UES. In addition, the time required for the numerical
inversion of the UES (rate of conversion of the iteration
process) varies significantly. It strongly depends on
inversion algorithm and on the choice of the initial
approximation for the salinity.</p>
      <p>To evaluate the accuracy of the NN approximation (4a)
and (4b), 16,000 points were generated within the domain D
on a grid, which did not include the training set points. The
density of seawater calculated from the UES (2) was
compared to that calculated from the NN, rNNðT ; S; ZÞ;
using Eq. (4a). Table 1 shows several statistical measures of
the differences (or errors) between the UES and the NN
estimates for density. In terms of the bias and the RMS
differences, the NN results for density clearly satisfy the
criterion mentioned earlier; both the bias and the RMS
values do not exceed the uncertainties indicated there and
are , 0.1 kg m23.</p>
      <p>To evaluate the errors in using the NN approach to
estimate the salinity, we used the same 16,000 points
ðri; Ti; Si; ZiÞ which were used to estimate the density.
Initially, the NN for SNN Eq. (4b) was applied to calculate a
new salinity, si; using the corresponding values ðTi; ri; ZiÞ:
Then the differences ðSi 2 siÞ were utilized to estimate the
accuracy of the NN-derived salinities (first row of Table 2).
To further evaluate the quality of the NN-derived salinities,
the UES was applied again, this time to the triad ðTi; si; ZiÞ to
recalculate the density of seawater, r0i: If the NN-obtained
values for salinity were perfect, then the density, r0i; would
be equal to ri: The differences between these two values,
ðri 2 r0iÞ; were then used to further estimate the accuracy of
the salinity-trained NN in terms of the density (second row
of Table 2).</p>
      <p>Table 2 shows that the NN estimates of salinity (4b) have
an RMS error of 0.1 psu. In terms of the related error in
density, this accuracy corresponds to an RMS error of
0.08 kg m23, which again does not exceed the uncertainties
discussed earlier.</p>
      <p>A substantial additional acceleration of calculations may
be achieved by the use of differential increments of density,
temperature, and salinity. Hence, we extend our approach to
estimate these quantities also. Additionally, an efficient way
of substantially reducing the computational burden is to
replace the calculations of density per se by calculations of
its total differential</p>
      <p>›r ›r
Dr ¼ ›T DT þ ›S DS</p>
      <p>Minimum, maximum, and mean errors together with the RMS errors are
presented.
where DT and DS are increments of T and S; ›r=›T ; and
›r=›S are functions of T ; S; and z: In this approach, after the
density and its derivatives are calculated, Eq. (6) is used
during several (usually several tens) steps of integration to
estimate the new density. Then the density and its
derivatives are recalculated, using the UES or NN
approximation of the UES, to update the estimated values
obtained using Eq. (6).</p>
      <p>The density and the derivatives ›r=›T and ›r=›S can be
accurately calculated from the NN rNN; Eq. (4a) (Fig. 2).
Thus, Eq. (6) can be reduced to
Dr ¼
›rNN DT þ
›T
›rNN DS
›S
ð7Þ
The estimation of the density using Eq. (6) requires several
calculations of the UES (in that case the Jacobians are
computed by centered finite differences). The estimation of
the density using Eq. (7) requires one estimate of the NN
(4a) and its derivatives, which is faster than Eq. (6). If
›rNN=›z is also used in Eq. (7) for vertical integration, the
gain in the speed of calculations due to the use of the NN
increases.</p>
      <p>Table 3 illustrates the accuracy of Jacobian calculations
using the NN parameterization (4a) with three neurons in
one hidden layer. All errors are estimated with respect to the
Jacobian calculated explicitly, using the UES (2). The
RMSN error is a relative error in percents with respect to
the norm of the corresponding derivative. Errors in
derivatives do not exceed 6%, which is acceptable for
calculation of density.</p>
      <p>
        The NN approach (7) is used in the high resolution
Multiscale Ocean Forecast System
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34 ref6">(Chalikov, Rao, Rivin,
Krasnopolsky, &amp; Grumbine, 2002)</xref>
        . This use of NN and its
Derivative Min error Max error Mean error RMS error RMSN error
›rNN=›T
›rNN=›S
›rNN=›z
      </p>
      <p>Minimum, maximum, and mean errors together with the RMS errors are
presented. RMSN error is the RMS error relative to the norm of the
corresponding derivative.
derivatives has been shown to accelerate the density
calculations about 10 times with the error in the density
calculations not exceeding the natural uncertainty
0.1 kg m23. Therefore, the computational expense of
calculating density has decreased from 40% to about 4 –
5% of the total time of integration as a result of using the NN
approximation in the model.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-5">
      <title>3. Atmospheric applications: NNs for efficient calculation of infrared radiative fluxes</title>
      <p>
        The next application that we present tackles the
problematic tradeoff between accuracy and speed in the
atmospheric infrared radiation computations. Transfer of
energy by infrared radiation significantly contributes to the
variations of atmospheric temperature. The infrared
atmospheric spectrum encompasses a wide range of variability,
from the slow-varying Planck function to the very detailed
structures of the individual absorption bands. As a
consequence, accurate modeling of the atmospheric
radiative processes requires a high spectral resolution, which
consumes a lot of computing time, and therefore can hardly
be used for simulation of the atmosphere. Radiation
computations also involve integrals over solid angle and
altitude, that cannot be analytically solved and therefore
significantly add to the computational burden. Two
strategies are used, often simultaneously, to make the
models affordable. On the one hand, statistical approaches
have been developed that simplify the calculations of the
three integrals (over solid angle, altitude and wave number)
and of the impact of clouds
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">(Goody &amp; Yung, 1989)</xref>
        . On the
other hand, the computations are not performed at every
time step and at every grid point of the atmospheric model
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14 ref37">(Morcrette, 2000)</xref>
        . As an example, in the NCEP forecast
model, infrared radiation variables are updated every 3 h
only.
      </p>
      <p>
        The computational efficiency is even more an issue in
elaborate 4D variational (4D-Var) analysis schemes.
These powerful data assimilation systems have been
developed in operational weather centers, like ECMWF
or Me´te´oFrance, to correct the atmospheric forecasts at
regular times with the observations that have been
received since the previous analysis: 4D-Var determines
a statistically optimum forecast, given the initial forecast
and its assumed error characteristics on the one side, and
the observations with their error specifications on the
other
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">(Courtier, The´paut, &amp; Hollingsworth, 1994)</xref>
        . To do
this, perturbations of the atmosphere need to be
propagated in time at every step of the minimization
process with a linearized physics. Only computationally
efficient parameterizations can be used for this purpose.
For instance, in the operational 4D-Var physics at
ECMWF, radiation perturbations are created by
temperature changes only. Neither water vapor nor cloud
evolution is taken into account
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">(Mahfouf, 1999)</xref>
        .
      </p>
      <p>
        NN-based radiative transfer models
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17 ref19 ref28 ref40">(Escobar-Munoz,
Che´din, Che´ruy, &amp; Scott, 1993; Faure, Isaka, &amp; Guillemet,
2001; Key &amp; Schweiger 1998; Schwander, Kaifel,
Ruggaber, &amp; Koepke, 2001)</xref>
        may be able to address these issues. In
particular, the NeuroFlux approach
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11 ref12 ref9">(Che´ruy, Chevallier,
Scott, &amp; Che´din, 1996; Chevallier, Che´ruy, Scott, &amp;
Che´din, 1998b)</xref>
        has been successively tested in the
Laboratoire de Me´te´orologie Dynamique climate model
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11 ref12 ref28 ref48">(Chevallier, Che´ruy, Li, &amp; Scott, 1998a)</xref>
        , in the ECMWF
forecast model
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10 ref14 ref37">(Chevallier, Morcrette, Che´ruy, &amp; Scott,
2000b)</xref>
        and is currently being tested in the ECMWF 4D-Var
system. This section describes the method, updates the
results and summarizes the experience gained by this
approach on which considerable effort has been invested.
      </p>
      <p>
        NeuroFlux is mainly a NN-based version of the
broadband radiation model of
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">Morcrette (1991)</xref>
        , hereafter
ECOPE, even though other models could be used in the
training. EC-OPE was the operational code at ECMWF in
the 1990s. The integration over wave number is performed
using a band emissivity method in six spectral regions
covering the long-wave spectrum. The transmission
functions for water vapor and carbon dioxide are fitted using
Pade´ approximants. Multi-layer gray bodies represent the
clouds
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47">(Washington &amp; Williamson, 1977)</xref>
        .
      </p>
      <p>NeuroFlux has been derived from EC-OPE using the
same cloud representation and the multi-layer perceptron.
Consistently with the former, upward and downward fluxes
are computed in NeuroFlux as
FðPiÞ ¼</p>
      <p>X akðPiÞ·FkðPiÞ
k
ð8Þ
where Pi is the pressure level, Fk the infrared flux in the
presence of a single layered black cloud in atmospheric
layer k or the clear-sky flux (with the convention k ¼ 0 for
clear sky), and ak is a weight. The aks are computed with a
simple parameterization as a function of the layered cloud
characteristics (cloud cover, liquid and ice water contents,
particle size, etc.) and depend on the way cloudy layers
overlap. In NeuroFlux, the Fks are computed with artificial
NNs with single hidden layers, whereas EC-OPE uses the
above-mentioned band-emissivity method.</p>
      <p>To summarize, NeuroFlux is made of a battery of
specialized NNs (one for each atmospheric layer k and for
each type of flux, upward or downward), the inputs of which
include the temperature and gas (water vapor and ozone)
profiles, the surface characteristics and the mean carbon
dioxide concentration, whereas the cloud characteristics are
processed by a separate parameterization. This way of doing
reduces the dimension of the individual NNs, compared to a
system where all computations would be performed by a
single NN. With that design, NeuroFlux is about eight times
faster than EC-OPE.</p>
      <p>
        The accuracy of NeuroFlux has been assessed through
code-by-code comparisons, climate simulations, and 10-day
forecasts. Figs. 3 and 4 illustrate the performance of the
version that fits the 50-level vertical resolution that was used
in the ECMWF operational forecast system in 1999. The
accuracy of NeuroFlux is comparable to the accuracy of
ECOPE, with a neutral impact on the simulations. In particular
the uncertainty introduced by NeuroFlux in the cloud cover
simulations was shown to be much smaller than that one
induced by the reduced temporal frequency of radiation
computation in the ECMWF climate simulations
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10 ref14 ref31 ref45">(Chevallier et al., 2000b)</xref>
        .
      </p>
      <p>Even though the inputs of the NNs in NeuroFlux do not
include the cloud profiles, some of the NNs reach sizes that
are unusually large. For instance, the NN that compute the
clear-sky upward fluxes in a 60-layer vertical grid contains
about 200 inputs and 60 outputs. As a consequence of this
huge variable space, the set up of the training datasets is
particularly involving. It relies on the sampling of hundreds
of thousands of atmospheric profiles with a simple topologic
approach, as described by Chevallier, Che´din, Che´ruy, and
Morcrette (2000a). Similar work is done each time the
vertical resolution is increased, because new levels are
expected to provide original information about the profiles
that cannot be obtained by a simple interpolation from the
lower resolution datasets. Each version of the training
datasets includes more than ten thousand profiles.</p>
      <p>
        Despite the large number of synoptic weights in
NeuroFlux, the partial derivatives of the computed fluxes
with respect to atmospheric variables (i.e. the Jacobians)
contain features that are considered not to be realistic
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">(Chevallier &amp; Mahfouf, 2001)</xref>
        . The characteristics of the
small noise of the computed fluxes (Fig. 3) show up in
the flux Jacobians. This is different from the behavior of the
smaller NNs presented in Section 2 (Table 3).
Regularization techniques, such as that one proposed by Aires,
Schmitt, Che´din, and Scott (1999), only partially improve
the quality of the NN computation. Larger NNs may solve
the problem, but would complicate the training even more
and would slow down the code, making it less attractive.
This issue of having correct sensitivities is very important
for the application to 4D-Var where linearizations of
the parameterizations are used. However, the approach of
NeuroFlux allows for an elegant solution. Eq. (8) is
differentiated as
dFðPiÞ ¼
      </p>
      <p>X akðPiÞ·dFkðPiÞ þ FkðPiÞ·dakðPiÞ
k
ð9Þ
Eq. (9) is used to calculate the flux perturbations. Its terms
are determined as follows. The aks and the Fks are obtained
from NeuroFlux. A pre-computed mean Jacobian matrix,
instead of the unsatisfactory NeuroFlux Jacobians, allows
for a reasonably accurate estimation of the dFks using a
firstorder Taylor approximation, since those partial fluxes are
weakly nonlinear. Finally, the daks are obtained analytically
from the tangent – linear version of the ak model.</p>
      <p>
        This approach is faster than the full tangent – linear
model of NeuroFlux by almost a twofold factor, which
makes it even more attractive. It is being evaluated as part of
an improved version of the 4D-Var linearized physics at
ECMWF, which introduces the treatment of the interaction
between cloud and radiation (Janiskova´, Mahfouf,
Morcrette, &amp; Chevallier, 2003). This package includes NeuroFlux,
a shortwave radiation model and a diagnostic cloud scheme,
on top of the currently operational simplified and linearized
physics. It is evaluated by studying the linearized time
evolution of analysis increments with reference to the
nonlinear computation using the full physics of the forecast
model. An improvement (respectively a degradation) of the
tangent – linear trajectory makes it closer to (respectively
further away from) the nonlinear one. Fig. 5 illustrates the
positive impact of the new physics on the wind increments
after a 12 h integration, with a global improvement of 3.3%.
Therefore the tangent – linear wind increments are more
realistic when the new physical package is used.
Preliminary results show a subsequent improvement of the forecast
quality
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">(Janiskova´ et al., 2002)</xref>
        .
      </p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-6">
      <title>4. Wave application: a NN approximation for nonlinear interactions in wind wave models</title>
      <p>
        Ocean wind wave modeling for hindcast and forecast
purposes has been at the center of interest of wave
forecasters for many decades. Numerical prediction models
are generally based on a form of the spectral energy or
action balance equation
DF
Dt ¼ Sin þ Snl þ Sds þ Ssw
where F is the spectrum, Sin the input source term, Snl the
nonlinear interaction source term, Sds the dissipation or
‘whitecapping’ source term, and Ssw represents additional
shallow water source terms. The JONSWAP study
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">(Hasselmann et al., 1973)</xref>
        identified the active role of the
nonlinear interactions in wave growth. The SWAMP study
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">(SWAMP Group, 1985)</xref>
        then identified the need for explicit
modeling of Snl in wave models. State-of-the-art or
socalled third generation wave models therefore explicitly
model this source term.
      </p>
      <p>
        In its full form
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24 ref26">(Hasselmann &amp; Hasselmann, 1985)</xref>
        , the
calculation of the interactions Snl requires the integration of
ð10Þ
nðk~Þ ¼ Fvðk~Þ ; v2 ¼ g·k·tanhðkhÞ
where the complicated coupling coefficient G contains
moving singularities
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">(Hasselmann, 1963)</xref>
        . This integration
requires roughly 103 – 104 times more computational effort
than all other aspects of the wave model combined.
Present operational constraints require that the
computational effort for the estimation of Snl should be of the
same order of magnitude as the remainder of the wave
model. This requirement was met with the development of
the DIA
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24 ref26">(Hasselmann et al., 1985)</xref>
        . The development of
the DIA allowed for the successful development of the
first third-generation wave model WAM
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29 ref46">(Komen et al.,
1994; WAMDI Group, 1988)</xref>
        . More than a decade of
experience with the WAM model and its derivatives has
identified shortcomings of the DIA. The DIA tends to
unrealistically increase the directional width of spectra,
has a systematic spurious impact on the shape of the
spectrum near the spectral peak frequency, and has a
much too strong signature at high frequencies. In present
third generation wave models, these deficiencies can be
countered at least in part by the dissipation source term
Sds; which is generally used for tuning the energy balance
in the Eq. (10). Although this approach often gives good
results, it is counterproductive, because it prohibits
development of dissipation source terms based on solid
physical considerations. With our increased understanding
in the physics of wave generation and dissipation, this
becomes an even bigger obstacle impeding further
development of third-generation wave models.
      </p>
      <p>
        Considering the above, it is of crucial importance for
the development of third generation wave models to
develop an economical yet accurate approximation for
Snl: Here, we explore a neural network interaction
approximation (NNIA) to achieve this goal
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32 ref33">(Krasnopolsky
et al., 2001; Krasnopolsky, Chalikov, &amp; Tolman, 2003)</xref>
        .
NNs can be applied here because the nonlinear interaction
(11) is essentially a nonlinear mapping (symbolically
represented in Eq. (11) by T) which relates two vectors
(2D fields in this case). Thus, the nonlinear interaction
source term can be considered as a nonlinear mapping
between a spectrum F and a source term Snl
Snl ¼ TðFÞ;
ð12Þ
where T is the exact nonlinear operator given by the full
Bolzmann interaction integral (11)
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24 ref26 ref39">(Hasselmann &amp;
Hasselmann, 1985; Resio &amp; Perrie, 1991)</xref>
        . Discretization
of S and F (as is necessary in any numerical approach)
reduces Eq. (12) to continuous mapping of two vectors of
finite dimensions. Modern high resolution wind wave
models use discretization on a 2D grid which leads to
dimensions of S and F vectors of order of N . 600
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42">(Tolman, 1999)</xref>
        . It seems unreasonable to develop a NN
approximation of such a high dimensionality (more than
600 inputs and outputs). Moreover, such a NN will be
grid dependent.
      </p>
      <p>In order to reduce the dimensionality of the NN and
convert the mapping (12) to a continuous mapping of two
finite vectors independent on the actual spectral
discretization, the spectrum F and source function Snl are expanded
using systems of 2D functions each of which (Fi and Cq)
creates a complete and orthogonal 2D basis</p>
      <p>n
F &lt; X xiFi;
i¼1</p>
      <p>m
Snl &lt; X yqCq;</p>
      <p>q¼1
where for xi and yq we have
xi ¼
ð ð FFi;
yq ¼
ð ð</p>
      <p>SnlCq;
where the double integral identifies integration over the
spectral space. Because both sets of basis functions
{Fi}i¼1;…;n and {Cq}q¼1;…;m are complete, increasing n
and m in Eq. (13) improves the accuracy of approximation,
and any spectrum F and source function Snl can be
approximated by Eq. (13) with a required accuracy.
Substituting Eq. (13) into Eq. (12) we can get
Y ¼ TðXÞ;
which represents a continuous mapping of the finite vectors
X [ Rn and Y [ Rm; and where T still represents the full
nonlinear interaction operator. This operator can be
approximated with a NN with n inputs and m outputs and
k neurons in the hidden layer
ð13Þ
ð14Þ
ð15Þ</p>
      <p>The accuracy of this approximation ðTNNÞ is determined by
k; and can generally be improved by increasing k:</p>
      <p>To train the NN approximation TNN of T; a training set
has to be created that consists of pairs of vectors X and Y:
To create this training set, a representative set of spectra
Fp has to be generated with corresponding (exact)
interactions Snl;p using Eq. (11). For each pair ðF; SnlÞp;
the corresponding vectors ðX; YÞp are determined using Eq.
(14). These pairs of vectors are then used to train the NN
to obtain TNN:</p>
      <p>After TNN has been obtained by training, the resulting
NN interaction approximation (NNIA) algorithm consists of
three steps: (1) decompose the input spectrum, F; by
applying Eq. (14) to calculate X; (2) estimate Y from X
using Eq. (16); and compose the output source function, Snl;
from Y using Eq. (13).</p>
      <p>A graphical representation of the NNIA algorithm
is shown in Fig. 6. Development of an actual NNIA
requires the following steps: (1) select basis functions Fi
and Cq and the number of each ðn; mÞ; (2) design a NN
topology (number of neurons k); (3) construct a
representative training set; and (4) select training
strategies.</p>
      <p>The first three points all have a significant impact on both
accuracy and economy of a NNIA. Unfortunately, there is
no pre-defined way to tackle these issues as mentioned in
Section 2. It is therefore unavoidable that the development
of a NNIA involves multiple iterations. The first
requirement for a NNIA to be potentially useful in operational
wave modeling is that the exact interactions Snl are closely
reproduced for computational costs comparable to that of
the DIA. The following shows the potential of this approach
with the design of a simple ad hoc NNIA.</p>
      <p>
        To address the basic feasibility of a NNIA, we have
considered a NNIA to estimate the nonlinear interactions
Snlðf ; uÞ as a function of frequency f and direction u from the
corresponding spectrum Fðf ; uÞ: Here we present the major
results of this study to illustrate our approach
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32 ref40">(Krasnopolsky
et al., 2001a)</xref>
        . To train and test this NNIA, we used a set of
about 20,000 simulated realistic spectra for Fðf ; uÞ; and the
corresponding exact estimates of Snlðf ; uÞ
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31 ref45">(Van Veldder
et al., 2000)</xref>
        . Comparison of simulated spectra with spectra
generated by the WAVEWATCH model
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42 ref43">(Tolman, 1999;
Tolman &amp; Chalikov, 1996)</xref>
        shows that the approach, which
we use for simulating spectra, allowed us to simulate
reasonably realistic and complicated spectra describing a
broad range of wave systems. Separate data sets have been
generated for training and validation.
      </p>
      <p>
        As is common in parametric spectral descriptions, we
choose separable basis functions where frequency and
angular dependencies are separated. For Fi this implies:
Fiðf ; uÞ ) Fij ¼ ff ;iðf Þfu;jðuÞ
ð17Þ
A similar separation is used for Cq: Considering the
strongly suppressed behavior of F and Snl for f ! 0; and the
quickly decreasing asymptotic behavior for f ! 1;
generalized Laguerre’s polynomials
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">(Abramowitz &amp; Stegun,
1964)</xref>
        are used to define ff and cf : Considering that no
directional preferences exist in F and Snl; Fourier
decomposition is used for fu and cu: The number of base functions is
chosen to be n ¼ 51 and m ¼ 64 to keep the accuracy of
approximation for F on average better than 2% and for Snl—
better than 5 – 6%. The number of hidden neurons was k ¼
30; which allows a satisfactory NN approximation of the
mapping (15) using Eq. (16).
      </p>
      <p>Table 4 compares three important statistics for the source
function RMS errors (with respect to exact solution)
calculated using DIA and NNIA for 10,000 spectra
(independent validation set). The NNIA is nearly twice as
accurate as DIA.</p>
      <p>Fig. 7 shows mean RMSE as functions of the frequency f
(left) and the angle u (right). It also illustrates the
improvement of the NNIA accuracy by increasing the
number of neurons, k; in the hidden layer from 20 to 30.
Numbers in Table 4 correspond to a NNIA with 30 neurons
in the hidden layer (51:30:64).</p>
      <p>And finally, Fig. 8 compares the DIA, NNIA, and exact
algorithms in terms of the accuracy and computational
efficiency. The current preliminary version of the NNIA
algorithm is twice as accurate and only about five times
slower than the DIA algorithm. In the current version of
Fig. 8. Comparison of the accuracy and computational efficiency of the
DIA, NNIA, and exact algorithms. The horizontal time scale is logarithmic.
the wind wave models, an algorithm that is up to 20 times
slower than DIA can be accommodated; therefore, we still
have enough room for further improving the accuracy of the
NNIA. Considering that no optimization has yet been
applied in the development of the NNIA composition and
decomposition procedures, it appears reasonable to expect a
final NNIA algorithm with computation requirements
similar to DIA but with significantly higher accuracy.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-7">
      <title>5. Summary and discussion</title>
      <p>In this paper we presented a recently emerged NN
application developed by the authors for simplifying and
accelerating time-consuming calculations in environmental
numerical models using NN techniques. Parameterizations
of physical, chemical, and biological processes, which occur
at different scales, constitute an important class of such
calculations. It is shown that, from a mathematical point of
view, descriptions of such processes can usually be
considered as continuous or almost continuous mappings
(dependencies between two vectors). It is known that NNs
are a generic tool for approximation of such mappings and,
therefore, can be used for fast and accurate approximation of
parameterizations of such processes. NNs can also easily
provide analytical Jacobians. Because the NN Jacobian is
computationally cheap, this approach is expected to be also
very beneficial when used in 3D and especially in 4D
variational data assimilation systems. We applied this
approach to four specific problems associated with oceanic,
atmospheric, and wave modeling.</p>
      <p>The first and second applications considered in the paper
deal with the oceanic equation of state, which is used for
estimating the density and salinity of seawater in ocean
circulation models. Separate NNs for density and salinity
were developed using the UES as a basis. Although the
estimation of density represents a forward problem,
estimating salinity from the UES represents a complicated
inverse problem, which has been very efficiently solved
using the NN approach. The accuracy of the NN-generated
densities and salinities were of the same order as those
obtained directly from the UES itself. However, the time
required to perform the calculations of density using the NN
and the neural network Jacobian is several times less than
that for UES. The time required for calculating salinity
using the NN is several hundred times less than that required
for the numerical inversion of the USE. Consequently, this
approach has direct application to numerical ocean models
where the equation of state must be estimated repeatedly. At
NCEP, a NN equation for seawater density is currently used
in an oceanic model.</p>
      <p>
        In the third application, the NN approach was shown to
successively handle the parameterization of infrared
radiation in atmospheric models and to improve the tradeoff
between speed and accuracy of such computation. In
particular, the scheme described allows speeding up
the computational time by a factor of eight compared to
the reference model, while not affecting the quality of
the atmosphere simulations. Further improvements of the
method include the use of a more accurate reference model
in the training phase, such as that currently operational at
ECMWF
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">(Morcrette, Mlawer, Iacono, &amp; Clough, 2001)</xref>
        .
The high number of variables involved in this NN
application made it necessary to develop original
approaches, such as for the set-up of the training dataset.
Also, the model computations are split into several modules,
each one of them being parameterized by a specific NN.
Despite this strategy, the NNs used are still very large,
which affects the quality of the Jacobians, because it makes
the training more difficult. Further increase of the vertical
resolution, or the introduction of additional input or output
variables, might further reduce the robustness of the model.
This is an obvious limitation in the framework of the
forecast models, which complexity constantly increases.
However, the approach appears to be suitable for the
variational assimilation, where other parts of the physics are
very simplified and where the speed factor is crucial. Also,
some other aspects of the radiation computation, such as the
cloud horizontal heterogeneity, are crudely handled by
forecast models and may benefit from NN
parameterizations, as illustrated by
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">Faure et al. (2001)</xref>
        .
      </p>
      <p>The fourth application deals with the nonlinear wave –
wave interactions in wind wave models. A prototype of the
NN approximation for this interaction is presented in this
work. The NNIA calculations of Snl are about five orders of
magnitude faster than the exact computation. The NNIA
calculations are twice more accurate than those from DIA
(oversimplified approximation, which is currently used in
the wind wave models) and require only 4 – 5 times more
computational effort than the DIA calculations with less
than 5% of this time spent in the actual NN part of the
algorithm. Decomposition of the input spectra F and
composing the source function Snl from the NN output
accounts for the rest. This decomposition (i) significantly
reduces the size of the NN and (ii) makes the approach
practically independent on the model grid and resolution.</p>
      <p>
        These four applications illustrate the strengths and
limitations of the NNs for the application to the fast
simulation of environmental processes. In the case of
retrievals, as discussed by
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">Krasnopolsky (1997)</xref>
        and
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">Krasnopolsky and Schiller (2003)</xref>
        , NNs compete with
other statistical methods, and usually perform better than
those. This is because NNs are able to optimize the
statistical link between the inputs and the outputs, provided
that a proper (i.e. diverse and regularly spread) training
dataset is gathered. In the present case, a sufficiently
accurate physically based direct model is usually available.
The NNs are likely to be faster, but significant speed gains
can also be obtained with more powerful computers, making
other parameterizations affordable. Also, the purely
statistical formulation of the NNs often makes the refinements
of their simulations, like additional inputs and outputs, or
more complex physics, more difficult than with an explicit
physics.
      </p>
      <p>The simulation of environmental processes may involve
a large number of inputs (i.e. several hundreds), which make
the NN too complex and complicates the training. For this
complexity problem, two possible solutions were developed
and illustrated: the input and output vectors may be
projected on a basis (e.g. the NNIA application) or a battery
of smaller NNs may be used (e.g. infrared radiation
application).</p>
      <p>
        Finally, a cheap computation of Jacobian is one of the
advantages of the NN approach. Using this Jacobian in a
combination with the tangent – linear approximation can
additionally accelerate calculations (e.g. the seawater
density application). However, since the Jacobian is not
trained, it is simply calculated through direct
differentiation of a trained NN. For large NNs (e.g. infrared
radiation application) the accuracy of the NN Jacobian
may not be sufficient for using with the tangent – linear
approximation. Several solutions can be offered for this
problem. First, the mean Jacobian can be calculated and
used (e.g. infrared radiation application). Second, the
Jacobian can be trained if included as actual additional
outputs in the NN or if trained as a separate additional
NN. This solution, however, leads to an increase of the
NN complexity or to additional time for the Jacobian
calculations. Third, regularization techniques can be used
to stabilize the Jacobians
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">(Aires et al., 1999)</xref>
        . For instance,
the error (or cost) function, which is minimized in the
process of the NN training, can be modified to
accommodate the Jacobian. Mathematically speaking, the
Euclidian norm, which is usually used for calculating the
error function, should be changed to the first order
Sobolev norm. With such a change the NN is trained to
approximate not only the function (as with the Euclidian
norm) but also the function’s first derivatives. Therefore, a
new error function E can be expressed as a superposition
of a standard error function E0 and a Jacobian error
function EJ
EJ ¼
      </p>
      <p>N
X
i
›FNN 2
›xi
›Ft 2
›xi
where ›Ft=›xi is the first derivative’s training value
calculated from the exact function to be approximated.
This solution does not change the number of the NN
outputs; however, it may require more hidden neurons and
may significantly complicate the minimization during the
training since the complexity of the error function
increases. As a consequence, the Jacobian modeling for
large NNs remains an open issue. This reflects the fact
that one way of improving the computational efficiency of
a direct model is to degrade the quality of the derivatives,
while keeping the direct model within a given noise.</p>
      <p>NNs obviously provide powerful solutions for
the simulation of environmental processes, but like any
other parameterization, their relevance needs to be
regularly re-evaluated with respect to the particular
computational and scientific contexts where they are
developed and used.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-8">
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We thank M. Janiskova´, at ECMWF for providing the
results of Fig. 5. We also thank D. Chalikov, D.B. Rao, and
H. Tolman, at NCEP for their help and support in
developing oceanic and wave NN applications.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Abramowitz</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Stegun</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>I. A</given-names>
          </string-name>
          . (Eds.), (
          <year>1964</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Handbook of mathematical functions with formulas, graphs and mathematical tables</article-title>
          .
          <source>National Bureau of Standards.</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Aires</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Schmitt</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Che´din,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
            , &amp;
            <surname>Scott</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>N. A.</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1999</year>
          ).
          <article-title>The weight smoothing regularization of MLP for Jacobian stabilization</article-title>
          .
          <source>IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks</source>
          ,
          <volume>10</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1502</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1510</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Apel</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J. R.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1987</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Principles of ocean physics</article-title>
          . New York: Academic Press, p.
          <fpage>145</fpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Attali</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.-G.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp; Page`s,
          <string-name>
            <surname>G.</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1997</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Approximations of functions by a multilayer perceptron: a new approach</article-title>
          .
          <source>Neural Networks</source>
          ,
          <volume>6</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1069</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1081</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Chalikov</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , et al. (
          <year>1998</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Revisiting the question of assimilating temperature alone into a full equation of state ocean model</article-title>
          .
          <source>Ocean Modeling</source>
          ,
          <volume>116</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>13</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>14</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Chalikov</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Rao</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>D. B.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Rivin</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>I.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Krasnopolsky</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>V.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Grumbine</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2002</year>
          ).
          <article-title>A multi-scale ocean forecast system for applications to global and regional domains</article-title>
          .
          <source>NCEP/NOAA Technical Note, OMB contribution No. 194</source>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Washington</surname>
            <given-names>DC</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , 130 pp.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1995a</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Approximation capability to functions of several variables, nonlinear functionals and operators by radial basis function neural networks</article-title>
          .
          <source>Neural Networks</source>
          ,
          <volume>6</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>904</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>910</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1995b</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Universal approximation to nonlinear operators by neural networks with arbitrary activation function and its application to dynamical systems</article-title>
          .
          <source>Neural Networks</source>
          ,
          <volume>6</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>911</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>917</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Che</surname>
            ´ruy,
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Chevallier</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Scott</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>N. A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp; Che´din,
          <string-name>
            <surname>A.</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1996</year>
          ).
          <article-title>A fast method using neural networks for computing the vertical distribution of the thermal component of the Earth radiative budget</article-title>
          . Comptes Rendus de l'
          <source>Acade´mie des Sciences de Paris 322(S. IIb)</source>
          ,
          <fpage>665</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>672</lpage>
          . in French.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Chevallier</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Che´din,
          <string-name>
            <surname>A.</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Che´ruy,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
            , &amp;
            <surname>Morcrette</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>J.-J.</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2000a</year>
          ).
          <article-title>TIGRlike atmospheric profile databases for accurate radiative flux computation</article-title>
          .
          <source>Quarterly Journal of the Royal Meteorological Society</source>
          ,
          <volume>126</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>761</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>776</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Chevallier</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Che´ruy,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
            ,
            <surname>Li</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Z.X.</given-names>
            , &amp;
            <surname>Scott</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>N.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>A (1998a). A fast and accurate neural network-based computation of longwave radiative budget application in a GCM</article-title>
          .
          <source>Proceedings of the American Meteorological Society Conference</source>
          , Paris, France,
          <fpage>25</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>29</lpage>
          Mai 1998 (pp.
          <fpage>690</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>693</lpage>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Chevallier</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Che´ruy,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
            ,
            <surname>Scott</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>N. A.</surname>
          </string-name>
          , &amp; Che´din,
          <string-name>
            <surname>A.</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1998b</year>
          ).
          <article-title>A neural network approach for a fast and accurate computation of longwave radiative budget</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Applied Meteorology</source>
          ,
          <volume>37</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1385</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1397</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Chevallier</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Mahfouf</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.-F.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Evaluation of the Jacobians of infrared radiation models for variational data assimilation</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Applied Meteorology</source>
          ,
          <volume>40</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1445</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1461</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Chevallier</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Morcrette</surname>
            , J.-J., Che´ruy,
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Scott</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>N. A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2000b</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Use of a neural-network-based longwave radiative transfer scheme in the EMMWF atmospheric model</article-title>
          .
          <source>Quarterly Journal of the Royal Meteorological Society</source>
          ,
          <volume>126</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>761</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>776</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Courtier</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , The´paut,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>J.-N.</given-names>
            , &amp;
            <surname>Hollingsworth</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>A.</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1994</year>
          ).
          <article-title>A strategy for operational implementation of 4D-Var, using an incremental approach</article-title>
          .
          <source>Quarterly Journal of the Royal Meteorological Society</source>
          ,
          <volume>120</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1367</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1388</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cybenko</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Approximation by superposition of sigmoidal functions</article-title>
          ,
          <source>in mathematics of control. Signals and Systems</source>
          ,
          <volume>2</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>303</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>314</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Escobar-Munoz</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Che´din,
          <string-name>
            <surname>A.</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Che´ruy,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
            , &amp;
            <surname>Scott</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>N. A.</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Re´seaux de neurones multi-couches pour la restitution de variables thermodynamiques atmosphe´riques e` l'aide de sondeurs verticaux satellitaires</article-title>
          . Comptes Rendus de l'Acade´mie´ des Sciences de Paris,
          <volume>317</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>911</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>918</lpage>
          . in French.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Estrade</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.-F.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Tre´molet,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            , &amp;
            <surname>Sela</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>J.</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Experiments with NCEP's Spectral Model</article-title>
          . In W. Zwieflhofer, &amp; N. Kreitz (Eds.),
          <source>Developments in Teracomputing-Proceedings of the Ninth ECMWF Workshop on the Use of High Performance Computing in Meteorology</source>
          , Reading, UK,
          <fpage>13</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>17</lpage>
          November 2000 (pp.
          <fpage>92</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>99</lpage>
          ). World Scientific Publishing Co.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Faure</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Isaka</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Guillemet</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Mapping neural network computation of high-resolution radiant fluxes of inhomogeneous clouds</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Geophysical Research</source>
          ,
          <volume>106</volume>
          (
          <issue>D14</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>14961</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>14974</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Fofonoff</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>N. P.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Millard</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>R. C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Jr.</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1983</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Algorithms for computation of fundamental properties of seawater</article-title>
          .
          <source>UNESCO technical paper in marine science 44</source>
          , UNESCO.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Funahashi</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          ).
          <article-title>On the approximate realization of continuous mappings by neural networks</article-title>
          .
          <source>Neural Networks</source>
          ,
          <volume>2</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>183</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>192</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Goody</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>R. M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Yung</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>Y. L.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Atmospheric radiation</article-title>
          . New York: Oxford University Press, 519 pp.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Hasselmann</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1963</year>
          ).
          <article-title>On the non-linear energy transfer in a gravity-wave spectrum. Part 3: evaluation of the energy flux and swell - sea interaction for a Neumann spectrum</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Fluid Mechanics</source>
          ,
          <volume>15</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>385</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>399</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref24">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Hasselmann</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Hasselmann</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1985</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Computations and parametrizations of the nonlinear energy transfer in a gravity wave spectrum. Part I: a new method for efficient computations of the exact nonlinear transfer integral</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Physical Oceanography</source>
          ,
          <fpage>1369</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1377</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref25">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Hasselmann</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , et al. (
          <year>1973</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Measurements of wind- wave growth and swell decay during the Joint North Sea Wave Project (JONSWAP). Erga¨nzungshelf zur Deutschen Hydrographischen Zeitschrift, Reihe A (8</article-title>
          ),
          <volume>12</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>95</fpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref26">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Hasselmann</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , et al. (
          <year>1985</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Computations and parametrizations of the nonlinear energy transfer in a gravity wave spectrum. Part II: parametrization of the nonlinear transfer for application in wave models</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Physical Oceanography</source>
          ,
          <volume>15</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1378</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1391</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref27">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Janiskova´</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Mahfouf</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.-F.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Morcrette</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.-J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Chevallier</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2002</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Linearized radiation and cloud schemes in the ECMWF model: development and evaluation</article-title>
          .
          <source>Quarterly Journal of the Royal Meteorological Society</source>
          ,
          <volume>128</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1505</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1528</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref28">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Key</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Schweiger</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A. J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1998</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Tools for atmospheric radiative transfer: streamer and fluxnet</article-title>
          .
          <source>Computer and Geosciences</source>
          ,
          <volume>24</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>443</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>451</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref29">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Komen</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>G. J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , et al. (
          <year>1994</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Dynamics and modelling of ocean wave</article-title>
          , Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 532 pp.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref30">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Krasnopolsky</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>V. M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1997</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Neural networks for standard and variational satellite retrievals</article-title>
          .
          <source>NCEP/NOAA Technical Note, OMB contribution No. 148</source>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Washington</surname>
            <given-names>DC</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , 43 pp.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref31">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Krasnopolsky</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>V. M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          et al (
          <year>2000</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Application of neural networks for efficient calculation of sea water density or salinity from the UNESCO equation of state</article-title>
          ,
          <source>Proceedings of the Second Conference on Artificial Intelligence</source>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>AMS</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Long Beach, CA,
          <fpage>9</fpage>
          -
          <issue>14</issue>
          <year>January</year>
          ,
          <year>2000</year>
          (pp.
          <fpage>27</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>30</lpage>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref32">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Krasnopolsky</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>V.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Chalikov</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>D. V.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tolman</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>H. L</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Using neural network for parameterization of nonlinear interactions in wind wave models</article-title>
          ,
          <source>International Joint Conference on Neural Networks, July 15 - 19</source>
          ,
          <year>2001</year>
          , Washington, DC (pp.
          <fpage>1421</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1425</lpage>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref33">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Krasnopolsky</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>V. M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Chalikov</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>D. V.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tolman</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>H. L.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2003</year>
          ).
          <article-title>A neural network technique to improve computational efficiency of numerical oceanic models</article-title>
          .
          <source>Ocean Modelling</source>
          ,
          <volume>4</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>363</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>383</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref34">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Krasnopolsky</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>V. M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Schiller</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2002</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Some neural network applications in environmental sciences. Part I: forward and inverse problems in satellite remote sensing</article-title>
          .
          <source>Neural Networks</source>
          ,
          <volume>16</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>321</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>334</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref35">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Mahfouf</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.-F.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1999</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Influence of physical processes on the tangent - linear approximation</article-title>
          . Tellus,
          <year>51A</year>
          ,
          <fpage>147</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>166</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref36">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Morcrette</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.-J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1991</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Radiation and cloud radiative properties in the ECMWF operational weather forecast model</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Geophysical Research</source>
          ,
          <year>96D</year>
          ,
          <fpage>9121</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>9132</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref37">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Morcrette</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.-J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2000</year>
          ).
          <article-title>On the effects of the temporal and spatial sampling of radiation fields on the ECMWF forecasts and analyses</article-title>
          .
          <source>Monthly Weather Review</source>
          ,
          <volume>128</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>876</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>887</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref38">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Morcrette</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.-J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Mlawer</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>E. J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Iacono</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Clough</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>S. A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Impact of the radiation-transfer scheme RRTM in the ECMWF forecasting system</article-title>
          .
          <source>ECMWF Newsletter</source>
          ,
          <volume>91</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>2</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref39">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Resio</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>D. T.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Perrie</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1991</year>
          ).
          <article-title>A numerical study of nonlinear energy fluxes due to wave - wave interactions, 1, methodology and basic results</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Fluid Mechechanics</source>
          ,
          <volume>223</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>603</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>629</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref40">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Schwander</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Kaifel</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Ruggaber</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Koepke</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Spectral radiative transfer modeling with minimized computation time by use of neural-network technique</article-title>
          .
          <source>Applied Optics</source>
          ,
          <volume>40</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>331</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>335</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref41">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>SWAMP Group</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1985</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Ocean wave modeling</article-title>
          . New York: Plenum Press, 256 pp.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref42">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tolman</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>H. L</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1999</year>
          ).
          <article-title>User manual and system documentation of WAVEWATCH-III version 1</article-title>
          .18, NOAA/NWS/NCEP/OMB
          <source>technical note 166</source>
          , 110 pp.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref43">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tolman</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>H. L.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Chalikov</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>D. V.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1996</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Source terms in a thirdgeneration wind wave model</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Physical Oceanography</source>
          ,
          <volume>26</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>2497</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>2518</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref44">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>UNESCO</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1981</year>
          ).
          <article-title>The practical salinity scale 1978 and the International Equation of State for Seawater 1980</article-title>
          .
          <source>Tenth Report of the Joint Panel on Oceanographic Tables and Standards</source>
          ,
          <source>UNESCO Technical Papers in Marine Science No. 36</source>
          , Paris, France: UNESCO.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref45">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Van Veldder</surname>
          </string-name>
          , et al (
          <year>2000</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Modelling of nonlinear quadruplet wave- wave interactions in operational coastal wave models, Abstract, accepted for presentation at ICCE 2000, Sydney</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref46">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>WAMDI Group</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          ).
          <article-title>The WAM model-a third generation ocean wave prediction model</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Physical Oceanography</source>
          ,
          <volume>18</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1775</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1810</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref47">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Washington</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>W. M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Williamson</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>D. L.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1977</year>
          ).
          <article-title>A description of the NCAR GCMs</article-title>
          . In J. Chang (Ed.),
          <source>General Circulation Models of the Atmosphere</source>
          (Vol.
          <volume>17</volume>
          ) (pp.
          <fpage>111</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>172</lpage>
          ).
          <source>Methods in Computational Physics</source>
          , New York: Academic Press.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref48">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Woodgate</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1998</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Can we assimilate temperature data alone into a full equation of state model?</article-title>
          <source>Ocean Modelling</source>
          ,
          <volume>114</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>4</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

