<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Neural Networks</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neunet.2006.01.003</article-id>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Temporal neural networks for downscaling climate variability * and extremes</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Yonas B. Dibike</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Paulin Coulibaly</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Department of Civil Engineering, School of Geography and Earth Sciences, McMaster University</institution>
          ,
          <addr-line>1280 Main Street West, Hamilton, Ont.</addr-line>
          ,
          <country country="CA">Canada</country>
          <addr-line>L8S 4L7</addr-line>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>19</volume>
      <issue>2006</issue>
      <fpage>135</fpage>
      <lpage>144</lpage>
      <abstract>
        <p>This paper presents an application of temporal neural networks for downscaling global climate models (GCMs) output. Because of computational constraints, GCMs are usually run at coarse grid resolution (in the order of 100s of kilometres) and as a result they are inherently unable to present local sub-grid scale features and dynamics. Consequently, outputs from these models cannot be used directly in many climate change impact studies. This research explored the issues of 'downscaling' the outputs of GCMs using a temporal neural network (TNN) approach. The method is proposed for downscaling daily precipitation and temperature series for a region in northern Quebec, Canada. The downscaling models are developed and validated using large-scale predictor variables derived from the National Center for Environmental Prediction (NCEP) reanalysis data set. The performance of the temporal neural network downscaling model is also compared to a regression-based statistical downscaling model with emphasis on their ability in reproducing the observed climate variability and extremes. The downscaling results for the base period (1961-2000) suggest that the TNN is an efficient method for downscaling both daily precipitation as well as daily maximum and minimum temperature series. Furthermore, the different model test results indicate that the TNN model mostly outperforms the statistical models for the downscaling of daily precipitation extremes and variability. q 2006 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved. * This work was made possible through a grant from the Canadian Climate Change Action Fund, Environment Canada, and a grant from the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada. The authors would like to thank the Aluminum Company of Canada (Alcan) for providing the experiment data. * Corresponding author. Tel.: C1 905 525 9140x23354; fax: C1 905 546 0463. E-mail address: couliba@mcmaster.ca (P. Coulibaly).</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Neural networks</kwd>
        <kwd>Downscaling</kwd>
        <kwd>Climate change</kwd>
        <kwd>Global climate models</kwd>
        <kwd>Climate variables</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>www.elsevier.com/locate/neunet</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>
        The mathematical models used to simulate the present
climate and project future climate with forcing by greenhouse
gases and aerosols are generally referred to as global climate
models (GCMs). However, the spatial resolution of GCMs
remains quite coarse, in the order of 100s of kilometres, and at
that scale, the regional and local details of the climate, which
are influenced by spatial heterogeneities in the regional
physiography, are lost. GCMs are therefore inherently unable
to represent local sub-grid scale features and dynamics, such as
local topographical features and convective cloud processes
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18 ref20">(Wigley, Jones, Briffa, &amp; Smith, 1990; Xu, 1999)</xref>
        . Therefore,
GCM simulations of local climate at individual grid points are
often poor especially when the area has complex topography
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">(Schubert, 1998)</xref>
        . However, in most climate change impact
studies, such as hydrological impacts of climate change, impact
models are usually required to simulate sub-grid scale
phenomenon and therefore require input data (such as
precipitation and temperature) at similar sub-grid scale. For
instance, precipitation scenarios at such finer temporal and
spatial resolution are needed in order to improve the design and
evaluate the future performance of urban drainage systems
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">(Bronstert, Niehoff, &amp; Bu¨ rger, 2002)</xref>
        . Therefore, there is the
need to convert the GCM outputs into at least a reliable daily
rainfall and temperature time series at the scale of the
watershed for which the hydrological impact is going to be
investigated. The methods used to convert GCM outputs into
local meteorological variables that are required for reliable
modeling of hydraulics and water recourses systems are usually
referred to as ‘downscaling’ techniques.
      </p>
      <p>
        There are various downscaling techniques available to
convert GCM outputs into daily meteorological variables
appropriate for hydrologic impact studies. The most widely
used statistical downscaling models usually implement linear
methods such as local scaling, multiple linear regression,
Canonical correlation analysis or singular value
decomposition
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11 ref14 ref2">(Conway, Wilby, &amp; Jones, 1996; Salathe, 2003;
Schubert &amp; Henderson-Sellers, 1997)</xref>
        . However, while
changes in the frequency and intensity of extreme events
are likely to have more of an impact on the environment and
human activities, most research works are focused mainly on
analyzing the ability of these downscaling models in
reproducing the average conditions of the present and future
climate events. Therefore, it is not yet clear which statistical
downscaling method provides the most reliable estimates of
daily rainfall and temperature as well as the intensity and
frequency of extreme climate events for the future horizon
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">(Xu, 1999)</xref>
        . Nevertheless, the interest in non-linear regression
methods, namely, artificial neural networks (ANNs), is
nowadays increasing because of their high potential for
complex, non-linear and time-varying input–output mapping.
Although the weights of an ANN are similar to non-linear
regression coefficients, the unique structure of the network
and the non-linear transfer function associated with each
hidden and output nodes allows ANNs to approximate highly
non-linear relationships without a priori assumption.
Moreover, while other regression techniques assume a functional
form, ANNs allow the data to define the functional form.
Therefore, ANNs are generally believed to be more powerful
than the other regression-based downscaling techniques
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">(von
Storch, Hewitson, &amp; Mearns, 2000)</xref>
        . The simplest form of
ANN (i.e. multi-layer perceptron) is reported to give similar
results compared to multiple regression downscaling methods
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">(Schoof &amp; Pryor, 2001)</xref>
        . It is also reported
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">(Weichert &amp;
Burger, 1998)</xref>
        that ANN models account better heavy rainfall
events, which may not be identified by a linear regression
downscaling technique. Nevertheless, some studies have also
shown that standard ANN method commonly used for
hydrologic variables modeling is not well suited to temporal
sequences processing, and often yield sub-optimal solutions
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3 ref4 ref5 ref9">(Coulibaly, Anctil, Aravena, &amp; Bobe´e, 2001a; Dibike &amp;
Coulibaly, 2005)</xref>
        . There are, however, other categories of
neural networks that have memory structure to account for
temporal relationships in the input–output mappings, and
they appear to be more suitable for complex non-linear
system modelling
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3 ref4 ref7 ref9">(Coulibaly, Anctil, Aravena, &amp; Bobe´e,
2001b; Gautam &amp; Holz, 2000)</xref>
        . More recently,
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">Tatli, Dalfes,
and Mente (2004</xref>
        ) proposed recurrent neural network of
Jordan type that uses not only large-scale predictors, but also
the previous states of the relevant local-scale variables.
      </p>
      <p>
        The purpose of this study is therefore to identify optimal
temporal neural networks that can capture the complex
relationship between selected large-scale predictors and
locally observed meteorological variables (or predictands).
Moreover, the paper aims to highlight the applicability of
temporal neural networks as downscaling methods for
improving daily precipitation and temperature estimates at
a local-scale with emphasis on its ability to capture climate
variability and extremes. The downscaling models are
developed and validated using large-scale predictor variables
derived from the National Center for Environmental
Prediction (NCEP) reanalysis data set. The paper specifically
focuses on the time lagged feed-forward neural networks
(TLFN), which have temporal processing capability without
resorting to complex and costly training methods. In
addition, emphasis is given to evaluating and comparing
the optimal TLFN method with the most commonly used
regression-based downscaling method and the best models
are applied to downscale the outputs of the Canadian global
climate model (CGCM1) forced with IPCC IS92a emission
scenario
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">(IPCC, 2001)</xref>
        .
      </p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>2. Downscaling methods: an overview</title>
      <p>
        Spatial ‘downscaling’ is the means of relating the
largescale atmospheric predictor variables simulated by GCMs to
local or station-scale meteorological records. There are a
variety of downscaling techniques in the literature, but two
major approaches can be identified at the moment, namely,
dynamic downscaling and empirical (statistical) downscaling.
Dynamic downscaling approach is a method of extracting
local-scale information by developing regional climate models
(RCMs) with the coarse GCM data used as boundary
conditions. Empirical downscaling, on the other hand, starts
with the premise that the regional climate is the result of
interplay of the overall atmospheric and oceanic circulation as
well as of regional topography, land–sea distribution and land
use
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">(von Storch et al., 2000)</xref>
        . As such, empirical downscaling
seeks to derive the local-scale information from the
largerscale climate variables through inference from the cross-scale
relationship using some random and/or deterministic functions.
Formally, the concept of regional climate being conditioned by
the large-scale state may be written as
(1)
R Z FðLÞ
where R represents the predictand (a regional or local climate
variable such as daily precipitation and temperature), L is the
predictor (a set of large-scale climate variables such as mean
sea level pressure, specific humidity, geopotential heights,
etc.), and F a deterministic/stochastic function conditioned by
L and has to be found empirically from observation or modeled
data sets. The predictor value L may be taken at the same time
as that of the predictand R or at some other time based on some
sort of correlation analysis.
      </p>
      <p>
        A diverse range of empirical downscaling techniques have
been developed over the past few years and individual
downscaling schemes differ according to the choice of
mathematical transfer function, predictor variables or
statistical fitting procedure. To date, linear and non-linear regression,
artificial neural networks, canonical correlation and principal
component analysis have all been used to derive predictor–
predictand relationships
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14 ref2">(Conway et al., 1996; Schubert &amp;
Henderson-Sellers, 1997)</xref>
        . One of the well-recognized
statistical downscaling tools that implements a regression-based
method is the statistical down-scaling model (SDSM)
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">(Wilby,
Dawson, &amp; Barrow, 2002)</xref>
        . SDSM is used in this study as a
benchmark model as it appears to be one of the most widely
used model for precipitation and temperature downscaling.
SDSM calculates statistical relationships, based on multiple
linear regression techniques, between large-scale (the
predictors) and local climate variables (the predictand). These
relationships are developed using observed weather data and,
assuming that these relationships remain valid in the future,
they can be used to obtain downscaled local information for
some future time period by driving the relationships with
predictors simulated by GCMs. Moreover, different types of
data transformations (e.g. logarithms, squares, cubes, fourth
powers) can be applied to the standard predictor variables prior
to downscaling model calibration to produce non-linear
regression models.
      </p>
      <p>While the main appeal of regression-based downscaling is
the relative ease of their application; however, these models
often explain only a fraction of the observed climate variability
(especially, when the predictand is precipitation). SDSM
implements bias correction and variance inflation techniques
to reduce the standard error of estimate and increase the
amount of variance explained by the model(s) to achieve the
best possible downscaling performance. However, some
preliminary studies have shown that SDSM is not as good in
reproducing climate variability and extremes as capturing the
average condition, especially when the predictand is
precipitation. This paper attempts to show the possibility of using
temporal neural network to improve downscaling results in
terms of reproducing climate variability and extremes.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-4">
      <title>3. Temporal neural network method</title>
      <p>
        A neural network can be characterized by its architecture,
which is represented by the network topology and pattern of
connections between the nodes, its method of determining the
connection weights, and the activation functions that it
employs. Multi-layer perceptrons (MLPs), which constitute
probably the most widely used network architecture, are
composed of a hierarchy of processing units organized in a
series of two or more mutually exclusive sets of neurons or
layers. The information flow in the network is restricted to a
flow, layer by layer, from the input to the output, hence also
called feed-forward network. However, in temporal problems,
measurements from physical systems are no longer an
independent set of input samples, but functions of time. To
exploit the time structure in the inputs, the neural network must
have access to this time dimension. While feed-forward, neural
networks are popular in many application areas, they are not
well suited for temporal sequences processing due to the lack
of time delay and/or feedback connections necessary to provide
a dynamic model. They can be used as pseudo-dynamic models
only by using successively lagging multiple inputs based on
correlation and mutual information analysis of the input data.
There are however various types of neural networks that have
internal memory structures that can store the past values of
input variables through time and there are different ways of
introducing ‘memory’ in a neural network in order to develop a
temporal neural network. Time lagged feed-forward networks
(TLFN) and recurrent networks (RNN) are the two major
groups of dynamic neural networks mostly used in time series
analysis
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3 ref4 ref6">(Coulibaly et al., 2001a,b; Dibike, Solomatine, &amp;
Abbott, 1999)</xref>
        . However, the latter require complex training
Fig. 1. Schematization of the Time lagged feed-forward neural network (TLFN)
with one hidden layer, one input variable and a delay-line with memory depth
of k.
algorithms and hence are computationally costly. The analysis
in this paper concerns temporal neural networks that can be
easily trained for practical application.
      </p>
      <p>Time lagged feed-forward neural network (TLFN) is a
neural network that can be formulated by replacing the neurons
in the input layer of an MLP with a memory structure, which is
sometimes called a tap delay-line. The size of the memory
layer (the tap delay) depends on the number of past samples
that are needed to describe the input characteristics in time and
it has to be determined on a case-by-case basis. TLFN uses
delay-line processing elements, which implement memory by
simply holding past samples of the input signal as shown in
Fig. 1. The output (y) of such a network with one hidden layer
is given by
yðnÞ Z 41</p>
      <p>Z 41
m
X wjyjðnÞ C b0
jZ1</p>
      <p>!
m
X wj42
jZ1</p>
      <p>k
X wjixðnK1Þ C bj
jZ0
!</p>
      <p>!
C b0
where m is the size of the hidden layer, n is the time step, wj is
the weight vector for the connection between the hidden and
output layers, wji is the weight matrix for the connection
between the input and hidden layers and f1 and f2 are transfer
functions at the output and hidden layers, respectively. bj and
b0 are additional network parameters (often called biases) to be
determined during training of the networks with observed
input/output data sets. For the case of multiple inputs (of size
p), the delay-line with a memory depth k can be represented by
cðnÞ Z ½XðnÞ; XðnK1Þ; .; XðnKk C 1Þ
where XðnÞZ ðx1ðnÞ; x2ðnÞ; .; xpðnÞÞ and represents the input
pattern at time step n, xj(n) is an individual input at the nth time
step and c(n) is the combined input matrix to the processing
elements at time step n. Such delay-line only ‘remembers’ k
samples in the past.</p>
      <p>
        An interesting feature of the TLFN is that the tap delay-line
at the input does not have any free parameters; therefore the
network can still be trained with the classical backpropagation
algorithm. The TLFN topology has been successfully used in
non-linear system identification, time series prediction
(2)
(3)
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3 ref4">(Coulibaly et al., 2001b)</xref>
        , and temporal pattern recognition
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">(Principe, Euliano, &amp; Lefebvre, 2000)</xref>
        . A major advantage of
the TLFN is that it is less complex than the conventional time
delay and recurrent networks and has the similar temporal
patterns processing capability
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">(Dibike et al., 1999)</xref>
        .
      </p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-5">
      <title>4. Study area and data</title>
      <p>
        The study area considered in this paper is the Serpent River
basin located in the Saguenay watershed (Fig. 2) of Quebec,
Canada. The basin has an area of 1760 km2 and is located in the
eastern part of the watershed. The meteorological station at
Chute-des-Passes (located at 49.98N, 71.258W) is the closest to
the Serpent River basin; therefore, the meteorological data
observed at this station is used for downscaling experiments.
Forty years of daily total precipitation as well as daily
maximum and minimum temperature records representing
the current climate (i.e. 1961–2000) were prepared for the
downscaling experiments. At the same time, observed daily
data of large-scale predictor variables representing the current
climate condition of the region is derived from the NCEP
reanalysis dataset
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">(Kistler et al., 2001)</xref>
        .
      </p>
      <p>Climate variables corresponding to the future climate
change scenario for the study area are extracted from the
Canadian global climate model (CGCM1). The atmospheric
component of the CGCM1 model has a surface grid resolution
of roughly 3.78!3.78 (400 km). The CGCM1 output used for
this study is the result of the IPCC ‘IS92a’ forcing scenario in
which the change in greenhouse gases forcing corresponds to
that observed from 1900 to 1990 and increases at a rate 1% per
year thereafter until year 2100. The direct effect of sulphate
aerosols is also included. CGCM1 outputs at the closest grid
point to the study area (508N, 718W) are used as inputs for the
downscaling models. The data is divided into four distinct
periods, namely, the current (covering the 40 years period
between 1961 and 2000), the 2020s (2010–2039), the 2050s
(2040–2069) and the 2080s (2070–2099). The NCEP-derived
predictor data have also been interpolated onto the same grid as
that of the CGCM1. All predictors in these data sets have been
normalized with respect to the 1961–1990 mean and standard
deviation and were made available by the Canadian Climate
Impacts Scenarios (CCIS) project.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-6">
      <title>5. Neural network design and training</title>
      <p>
        The neural network models in this study are developed
using the Neuro-Solutions neural networks development
environment
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">(Principe et al., 2000)</xref>
        . Inputs to the neural
networks are the 25 predictor variables derived from the
NCEP reanalysis dataset which are presented in Table 1 while
the outputs are daily precipitation amounts, and daily
maximum and minimum temperatures observed in the study
area. All the three climate variables are modeled separately.
First, TLFNs with different lag time (time delay) are trained
with all (the 22) predictor variables as input to the networks
and the best performing network is selected. Hyperbolic
tangent activation function is used at both the hidden and
output layers of the neural networks and the networks are
trained using a variation of backpropation algorithm
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">(Principe
et al., 2000)</xref>
        . In order to increase the generalizing ability of the
trained networks, the most relevant input variables (predictors)
are identified by performing sensitivity analysis on the selected
TLFN. Sensitivity analysis provides a measure of the relative
importance among the predictors (inputs of the neural network)
by calculating how the model output varies in response to
variation of an input. The relative sensitivity of the model to
each input is calculated by dividing the standard deviation of
the output by the standard deviation of the input, which is
varied to create the output. The results provide a measure of the
relative importance of each input (predictor) in the particular
input–output transformation. The network is then retrained
with the few selected (most relevant) predictor variables.
Several training experiments are conducted with different
combinations of time lags and number of neurons in the hidden
layer till the optimum network is identified. For the case of
downscaling of precipitation with TLFN, a time lag of 6 (days)
and 20 neurons in the hidden layer gave the best performing
network. In the case of temperature downscaling, TLFN with a
time lag of 3 (days) and 12 neurons in the hidden layer has
performed the best. This suggests that the predictand–
predictors relationship is less complex in the case of
temperature downscaling.
      </p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-7">
      <title>6. Downscaling results</title>
      <p>From the 40 years of observed data representing the current
climate, the first 30 years (1961–1990) are considered for
calibrating the downscaling models while the remaining 10
years of data (1991–2000) are used to validate those models.
The different parameters of each model are adjusted during
calibration to get the best statistical agreement between
observed and simulated meteorological variables. During the
calibration of precipitation downscaling models, in addition to
the mean daily precipitation and daily precipitation variability
for each month, monthly average dry and wet-spell lengths
constituted the performance criteria. For the cases of Tmax and
Tmin, mean and variances of these variables corresponding to
each month were considered as performance criteria.</p>
      <p>For both SDSM and TLFN, selecting the most relevant
predictor variables (set of inputs) is the first and important task
in the downscaling process. In the case of SDSM, the screening
is achieved with linear correlation analysis and scatter plots
(between the predictors and the predictand variables).
Observed daily data of large-scale predictor variables (NCEP
data) is used to investigate the percentage of variance
explained by each predictand–predictor pairs. For the TLFN,
the predictor variables are selected using sensitivity analysis as
described earlier. Even though the set of variables selected to
each of the downscaling methods is not identical, some
variables such as specific humidity at 500 hPa geopotential
height, near surface meridional wind velocity component,
850 hPa geopotential height and mean temperature at 2 m are
identified as relevant input by most of the downscaling
methods. A complete list of the most relevant predictor
variables selected as input for downscaling each
meteorological variable with the two downscaling methods is presented in
Table 2.
6.1. Validation results in downscaling NCEP data</p>
      <p>To assess the accuracy of the downscaling models, the
downscaling model validation statistics are presented in
Table 3 in terms of seasonal model biases. These validation
results indicate that except for the winter, the TLFN performed
better than SDSM model in downscaling daily precipitation.
More interestingly, during the autumn season—which is the
Prec.
main rainfall season in the region, the TLFN appears
particularly more suitable than the SDSM model for
downscaling daily precipitation. At the same time, both methods
demonstrated good and comparable performance in
downscaling daily maximum and minimum temperature values.</p>
      <p>Moreover, additional precipitation and temperature extreme
indices have been used to evaluate the performance of
statistical downscaling models in capturing the extreme indices
of these climate variables. Figs. 3–5 shows plots of observed
versus downscaled seasonal values for the 90th percentiles of
precipitation (Prec90) and daily maximum temperature
(Tmax90) and the 10th percentile of daily minimum temperature
(Tmin10) calculated for each of the 10 years of data including
both the calibration (the first 30 years) and validation (the last
1
X
X</p>
      <p>X
9</p>
      <p>12
20
9</p>
      <p>12
15
20
(a)
d
e
l
a
c
s
n
ow-6
D
25</p>
      <p>30
25
3</p>
      <p>6
-25</p>
      <p>-25
-30
-35
-40
5
30
25
-30
(b)</p>
      <p>-25
d
e
l
a
c
s
n
w
o
D
d
e
l
a
c
s
n
w
o
D
-20</p>
      <p>(d)</p>
      <sec id="sec-7-1">
        <title>Autumn -15 -10</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-7-2">
        <title>Spring</title>
        <p>-20
-15
-15
-20
-25
-30
-10
-15
-20
-5
-5
25
30
35</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-7-3">
        <title>Observed 15 20</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-7-4">
        <title>Observed</title>
        <p>Fig. 5. Observed versus downscaled (with SDSM and TLFN) data of the 10th percentile daily minimum temperature values (8C) for each season (a-winter, b-spring,
c-summer and d-autumn). Solid symbols correspond to the data downscaled with TLFN while the open symbols corresponds to the data downscaled with SDSM.
10 years) periods. The 90th percentile represent the values of
daily precipitation and Tmax which are not exceeded 90% of the
time (or are exceeded only 10% of the time) while the 10th
percentile represent the values of daily Tmin which are not
exceeded only 10% of the time (or are exceeded 90% of the
time). The best downscaling is the one with its extreme indices
laying closer to the 458 line when plotted on the graphs (Figs.
3–5). Accordingly, the plots on Fig. 3 show that the
TLFNdownscaling of daily precipitation resulted in a better
estimation of the Prec90 values in all the seasons except that
of summer. The plots on Figs. 4 and 5 also show that the
performance of TLFN in terms of Tmax90 and Tmin10 is
comparable to that of SDSM for all of the four seasons.
6.2. Downscaling GCM outputs corresponding to a future
climate scenario</p>
        <p>Once the downscaling models have been calibrated and
validated, the next step is to use these models to downscale the
future climate change scenario simulated by the GCM. In this
case, instead of the NCEP reanalysis data used as input to each
of the downscaling models earlier, the large-scale predictor
variables are taken from CGCM1 simulation output covering
the four distinct periods corresponding to ‘business as usual’
scenario explained earlier. The monthly statistics of current
observed values and the current and future CGCM1
simulations downscaled with TLFN and SDSM are
summarized and plotted in Figs. 6 and 7. Fig. 6a shows that the monthly
mean values of observed precipitation are quite close to that of
the TLFN-downscaled data of the current time period (1961–
2000) while Fig. 6b revels that the standard deviation of the
downscaled data are slightly lower than the observed one. This
indicates that the CGCM1 data downscaled with TLFN slightly
underestimate the variability of the local precipitation. Fig. 6a
and b also shows an increase both in the mean daily
precipitation and precipitation variability between the current
and the future time periods for almost all months of the year.</p>
        <p>Similarly, Fig. 7a and b show that while the monthly means of
the TLFN-downscaled temperature data for the current (1961–
2000) time period are comparable to that of the observed data,
they also show a consistently increasing trend in the
downscaled values of both the Tmax and Tmin values. No significant
trend is observed when it comes to the variability of monthly
Tmax and Tmin values. Table 4 summarizes the downscaling
results by presenting the simulated increase or decrease in
seasonal values of average precipitation and daily maximum
and minimum temperatures between the current (1961–2000)
and the 2080s (2070–2100) time periods for each of the
downscaling methods. The results show that both SDSM and
TLFN predicted a significant increase in precipitation.</p>
        <p>However, while TLFN predicted a seasonal variation in
precipitation increase (with around 16% increase in summer</p>
        <sec id="sec-7-4-1">
          <title>Precipitation Scenario Downscaled with TLFN J F M</title>
          <p>A
M
A
S
O
N
D
J</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-7-4-2">
          <title>Month J</title>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-7-4-3">
          <title>Current</title>
          <p>2020s
2050s
2080s</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-7-4-4">
          <title>Observed</title>
          <p>Precipitation Scenario Downscaled with TLFN
6
)
m
( 4
m
.
c
e
r
p
y
l
ia 2
d
n
a
e
M0
12
10
.
v
de 8
d
ra 6
d
n
tsa 4
.
rce 2
p
0
J</p>
          <p>F</p>
          <p>M</p>
          <p>A</p>
          <p>M</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-7-4-5">
          <title>Current 2020s J</title>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-7-4-6">
          <title>Month 2050s J A</title>
          <p>S
O
N
D
2080s</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-7-4-7">
          <title>Observed</title>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-7-4-8">
          <title>Tmax Scenario Downscaled with TLFN J F M</title>
          <p>A
M
A
S
O
N
D</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-7-4-9">
          <title>Current 2020s 2080s Observed</title>
          <p>to around 54% in winter), SDSM resulted in a smaller seasonal
variation of between 34% in winter and 49% in spring.</p>
          <p>In general, while SDSM-downscaled data resulted in an
increase of annual precipitation by about 44% by the 2080s, the
TLFN-downscaled data resulted in an increase of about 27.6%.
At the same time, downscaling result for daily Tmax and
Tmin values corresponding to both downscaling models show
a comparable and consistently increasing trend. For both the
Tmax and Tmin, the highest increase is predicted for the winter
season, ranging between 5.5 and 7.1 8C, while the lowest
increase is predicted for the autumn season ranging between
2.2 and 3.8 8C. Overall, downscaling with TLFN resulted in a
slightly higher increase in temperature than SDSM. In general,
the results suggest an average increase of 4–5 8C in the mean
annual temperature values for the next 100 years. This typically
implies major changes in the hydrologic regime particularly for
cold and snowy region like the Serpent River basin considered
in this study.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-8">
      <title>7. Conclusion</title>
      <p>This study investigates the applicability of temporal
neural networks as downscaling method for the generation
of daily precipitation and temperature series at the
Chutedes–Passes station located in the Saguenay watershed in
Canada and compares the results with that of the most
widely used multiple linear regression (SDSM) method. The
study results show that the time lagged feed-forward network
(TLFN) can be an effective method for downscaling daily
precipitation and temperature data as compared to the
commonly used method. The main advantage of this
downscaling method is its ability to incorporate not only
the concurrent, but also several antecedent predictor values
as input and its temporal processing ability without any
additional effort. The validation results in terms of biases and
the plots of extreme climate indices of the observed and
downscaled data showed that the TLFN is able to reproduce
the observed mean and extremes of each climate variables
as good as that of SDSM. In fact, TLFN performance
in downscaling precipitation for most of the seasons was
better than that of SDSM.</p>
      <p>The downscaling results corresponding to the future
‘business as usual’ climate change scenario show that while
the TLFN model has estimated an increase in average annual
precipitation by about 27.6% by the 2080s, the SDSM
estimated an increase in annual precipitation by about 44%
during the same time period. At the same time, downscaling
result for daily temperature corresponding to both models show
a comparable and consistently increasing trend, with the mean
annual temperature increase ranging between 4 and 5 8C for the
next 100 years. The results also show seasonal variation in the
changes with the biggest increase in temperature being in
winter and the smallest in autumn.</p>
      <p>However, one should also remember that all the
downscaling experiments in this study use the outputs from only one
general circulation model (CGCM1). Previous studies showed
that data taken from different GCMs could produce
significantly different downscaling outputs. Therefore, caution
should be exercised in interpreting the outcome of such
downscaling experiments for practical applications.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Bronstert</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Niehoff</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp; Bu¨rger, G. (
          <year>2002</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Effects of climate and land-use change on storm runoff generation: Present knowledge and modelling capabilities</article-title>
          .
          <source>Hydrological Processes</source>
          ,
          <volume>16</volume>
          (
          <issue>2</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>509</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>529</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Conway</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Wilby</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>R. L.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Jones</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>P. D.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1996</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Precipitation and air flow indices over the British Isles</article-title>
          .
          <source>Climate Research</source>
          ,
          <volume>7</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>169</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>183</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Coulibaly</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Anctil</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Aravena</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp; Bobe´e,
          <string-name>
            <surname>B.</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
          <article-title>ANN modeling of water table depth fluctuations</article-title>
          .
          <source>Water Resources Research</source>
          ,
          <volume>37</volume>
          (
          <issue>4</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>885</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>896</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Coulibaly</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Anctil</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp; Bobe´e,
          <string-name>
            <surname>B.</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Multivariate reservoir inflow forecasting using temporal neural networks</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Hydrologic Engineering</source>
          , ASCE,
          <volume>6</volume>
          (
          <issue>5</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>367</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>376</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Dibike</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>Y. B.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Coulibaly</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2005</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Hydrologic impact of climate change in the Saguenay watershed: Comparison of downscaling methods and hydrologic models</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Hydrology</source>
          ,
          <volume>307</volume>
          (
          <issue>1-4</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>145</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>163</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Dibike</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>Y. B.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Solomatine</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Abbott</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>M. B.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1999</year>
          ).
          <article-title>On the encapsulation of numerical-hydraulic models in artificial neural network</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Hydraulic Research</source>
          ,
          <volume>37</volume>
          (
          <issue>2</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>147</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>161</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Gautam</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>D. K.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Holz</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>K.-P.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2000</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Neural network based system identification approach for the modelling of water resources and environmental systems</article-title>
          . In O. Schleider, &amp; A.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Zijderveld</surname>
          </string-name>
          (Eds.),
          <source>Artificial intelligence methods in civil engineering applications</source>
          (pp.
          <fpage>87</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>100</lpage>
          ). Germany: Cottbus.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>IPCC</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
          <source>Climate change</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          :
          <article-title>The scientific basis</article-title>
          . Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Kistler</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>R. E.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Kalnay</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Collins,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
            ,
            <surname>Saha</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
            ,
            <surname>White</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
            ,
            <surname>Woollen</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
            ,
            <surname>Chelliah</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
            ,
            <surname>Ebisuzaki</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
            ,
            <surname>Kanamitsu</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
            ,
            <surname>Kousky</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>V.</given-names>
            ,
            <surname>Dool</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>H. V. D.</given-names>
            ,
            <surname>Jenne</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
            , &amp;
            <surname>Fiorino</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>M.</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
          <article-title>The NCEP/NCAR 50-year reanalysis</article-title>
          .
          <source>Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society</source>
          ,
          <volume>82</volume>
          (
          <issue>2</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>247</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>267</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Principe</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J. C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Euliano</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>N. R.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Lefebvre</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>W. C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2000</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Neural and adaptive systems: Fundamentals through simulations</article-title>
          . New York: Wiley.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Salathe</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>E. P.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2003</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Comparison of various precipitation downscaling methods for the simulation of streamflow in a rainshadow river basin</article-title>
          .
          <source>International Journal of Climatology</source>
          ,
          <volume>23</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>887</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>901</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Schoof</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J. T.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Pryor</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>S. C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Downscaling temperature and precipitation: A comparison of regression-based methods and artificial neural networks</article-title>
          .
          <source>International Journal of Climatology</source>
          ,
          <volume>21</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>773</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>790</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Schubert</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1998</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Downscaling local extreme temperature changes in southeastern Australia from the CSIRO Mark2 GCM</article-title>
          .
          <source>International Journal of Climatology</source>
          ,
          <volume>18</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1419</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1438</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Schubert</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Henderson-Sellers</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1997</year>
          ).
          <article-title>A statistical model to downscale local daily temperature extremes from synoptic-scale atmospheric circulation patterns in the Australian region</article-title>
          .
          <source>Climate Dynamics</source>
          ,
          <volume>13</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>223</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>234</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tatli</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Dalfes</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Mente</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2004</year>
          ).
          <article-title>A statistical downscaling method for monthly total precipitation over Turkey</article-title>
          .
          <source>International Journal of Climatology</source>
          ,
          <volume>24</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>161</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>180</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>von Storch</surname>
          </string-name>
          , H.,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Hewitson</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Mearns</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2000</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Review of empirical downscaling techniques</article-title>
          . In T. Iversen &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>B. A. K. Høiskar</surname>
          </string-name>
          (Eds.),
          <article-title>Regional climate development under global warming</article-title>
          .
          <source>General technical report no. 4. Conference proceedings regclim spring meeting Jevnaker</source>
          , Torbjørnrud, Norway (pp.
          <fpage>29</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>46</lpage>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Weichert</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Burger</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1998</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Linear versus nonlinear techniques in downscaling</article-title>
          .
          <source>Climate Research</source>
          ,
          <volume>10</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>83</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>93</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Wigley</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>T. M. L.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Jones</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>P. D.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Briffa</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Smith</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1990</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Obtaining subgrid scale information from coarse-resolution general circulation model output</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Geophysical Research</source>
          ,
          <volume>95</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1943</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1953</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Wilby</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>R. L.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Dawson</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>C. W.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Barrow</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>E. M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2002</year>
          ).
          <article-title>SDSM-A decision support tool for the assessment of regional climate change impacts</article-title>
          .
          <source>Environmental Modelling and Software</source>
          ,
          <volume>17</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>147</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>159</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>C. Y.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1999</year>
          ).
          <article-title>From GCM to river flow: A review of downscaling methods and hydrologic modeling approaches</article-title>
          .
          <source>Progress in Physical Geography</source>
          ,
          <volume>23</volume>
          (
          <issue>2</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>229</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>249</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

