<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Comparison between the real solution and the solution generated by our system. We highlight the best result for each indicator.
Solution Truck Containers Duration (s) Distance (m) Collected (kg)
Small</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>BIN-CT: Urban Waste Collection based on Predicting the Container Fill Level</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Javier Ferrer</string-name>
          <email>ferrer@lcc.uma.es</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Enrique Alba</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Dept. Lenguajes y Ciencias de la Computación, University of Malaga</institution>
          ,
          <country country="ES">Spain</country>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <volume>31</volume>
      <issue>12</issue>
      <abstract>
        <p>The fast demographic growth, together with the population concentration in cities and the increasing amount of daily waste, are factors that are pushing to the limit the ability of waste assimilation by Nature. Therefore, we need technological means to optimally manage of the waste collection process, which represents 70% of the operational cost in waste treatment. In this article, we present a free intelligent software system called BIN-CT (BIN for the CiTy), based on computational learning algorithms, which plans the 9best routes for waste collection supported by past (historical) and future (predictions) data. 1The objective of the system is to reduction the cost of the waste collection service minimizing the distance traveled by a truck to 0collect the waste from a container, thereby reducing the fuel consumption. At the same time the quality of service for the citizen 2 is increased, avoiding the annoying overflows of containers thanks to the accurate fill-level predictions given by BIN-CT. In this r particle we show the features of our software system, illustrating its operation with a real case study of a Spanish city. We conclude that the use of BIN-CT avoids unnecessary trips to containers, reduces the distance traveled to collect a container by 20%, and generates routes 33.2% shorter than the routes used by the company. Therefore it enables a considerable reduction of total costs A 2and harmful emissions thrown up into the atmosphere. 2</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>
        A
.1. Introduction
s
c
[ Waste generation is globally growing at an unstoppable rate,
in contrast, the assimilation capacity of our planet is
decreas2ing, turning waste treatment into a complex challenge we need
v
3to address as a modern society
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">(Al-Salem et al., 2009)</xref>
        . In
addi0tion, the linear structure of our economy (extract, manufacture,
6use and disposal) has reached its limits; the Earth is exhausted,
1natural resources are drained. The unsustainable development
.0of most nations has created a problem due to the growing
gen7eration of waste that must be solved. Despite the social and
0governmental commitment, there are hardly any technological
8means to optimise the management of the waste collection
pro1
:cess. The largest resources are needed to collect the municipal
ivwaste, which is mainly created by household, industrial, and
commercial activity.
      </p>
      <p>X
r Traditionally solid waste collection was carried out without
apreviously analyzing the demand or the routes of the vehicles
and the decisions about the routes were made by the drivers,
although the solutions were far from optimal. Solid waste
collection is usually undertaken based on static plans, with a
predetermined number of trips per week, designed manually in
most cases. This approach has severe limitations due to the
number of constraints to consider when finding an optimal
solution. Moreover, waste collection planning problems are
influenced by stochastic waste generation, tra c conditions, and
Preprint submitted to Elsevier
many constraints, which are unmanageable by a person, so the
use of an automatic tool to solve these types of problems is
mandatory.</p>
      <p>In this article we propose an intelligent software system,
called BIN-CT, for the management of solid waste collection
in an urban area. The system is doubly intelligent, since it
integrates algorithms to predict the fill level of waste containers,
plus the subsequent optimal generation of routes for collection
trucks. In other words, our software system solves the two
major problems that a waste collection service face: 1) what
containers should be collected and 2) in what order should the
containers be visited to minimize the cost.</p>
      <p>In order to solve the first question, we will use computational
machine learning techniques to estimate the fill level of each
container. Supported by historical data (past data), the system
generates predictions (future data) to decide when a container
should be collected. This prediction could be performed long
term or short term, considering seasonality, weekends, and
holidays. We want to highlight that, as far as we know, the
fill-level prediction of all containers individually (fine grain)
is a feature, which until now, has not been implemented in
any tool for waste collection management. Additionally, our
software system is able to interact with an Internet of Things
(IoT) system to obtain the actual filling of the containers
equipped with volumetric sensors. Moreover, the sensors’
information will be essential in the near future to validate the
historical data (obtained by truck drivers).</p>
      <p>
        Route generation (of waste collection in our case) is a
wellknown combinatorial problem called the Vehicle Routing
Problem (VRP)
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">(Dantzig and Ramser, 1959)</xref>
        . However the use of
historical data, predictions and the intelligent decisions about
the inclusion/exclusion of containers mean that it is not a
simple VRP. The solutions to our problem are usually constrained
by many factors. Some of them are the number of available
trucks, the trucks’ capacity, the amount of waste to collect and
the characteristics of the street where the container is placed
(too narrow for a big truck), among others. The planning of
waste collection routes has a wide number of variants and
constraints which makes it unmanageable for one person alone. In
contrast, there is great room for improvement using automatic
algorithms to deal with this problem. The improvement results
in lower cost services, a reduction of harmful emissions and a
better service for citizens, in quality and costs.
      </p>
      <p>
        In addition, we must take into account that the current city
system itself is under discussion. Many local authorities have
been forced to examine its cost-e ectiveness and
environmental impact since we have a system based on static collection
frequencies (once a week, twice a week, daily. . . ) that sometimes
results in unnecessary trips to semi-empty containers. The
pollution generated by these trips could be more dangerous for the
environment than the benefits of the collection. This is
especially critical in the case of selective collection (plastic, paper,
glass. . . ), where the waste volume is smaller than in the case of
organic waste. So, when you are dealing with recyclable waste,
the planning of optimal collection routes is even more
influential. Presently, the recyclable waste collection process
represents 70% of the operational cost of waste treatment
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">(Teixeira
et al., 2004)</xref>
        . The main objective of the work presented here
is the reduction of the collection process cost and is essentially
dependent on the distance travelled by the collection trucks.
      </p>
      <p>In Figure 1 we show the steps followed to solve the
problem we face in this article. The main phases are as follows:
First, all the data needed to solve the problem is treated and
stored in a database. In this way, the BIN-CT system is able to
load the information from the database instead of using several
large files. In the second phase, the software system uses the
historical fill-level data of each container and generates the
filllevel predictions. In the third step, the software system decides
which containers are going to be included in the next routes.
The decision is taken according to a given criterion based on
the predictions and estimated fill levels. In the fourth phase the
route algorithm computes optimal solutions, i.e., the complete
routes that the trucks must follow to collect the containers
selected in the previous step. Finally, the best solution is shown
on a navigable map in a web browser.</p>
      <p>The main contributions of this article are as follows:
We propose an intelligent system called BIN-CT for
generating optimal waste collection routes.</p>
      <p>We compare three machine-learning algorithms for the
forecasting of filling levels of each container (fine grain)
from historical data.</p>
      <p>We use a new real case study of a city with 217 containers
to illustrate the behavior of the proposed system.</p>
      <p>We compare the results obtained by BIN-CT to the results
of a real company in a real-world case study.</p>
      <p>The remainder of the article is as follows. In Section 2 we
describe work related to waste collection optimization, especially
the di erent variants studied in the literature. Section 3
describes the waste collection problem we address in this article.
Section 4 explains our proposal, the BIN-CT software system.
The four modules that comprise our software system are
described and we outline the most important features of the
system. Our experimental setup is presented in Section 5, then we
describe the real-world case study, and analyze the results of
two di erent experiments. Finally, we present our conclusions
and future work in Section 6.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>2. Related Work</title>
      <p>
        Waste collection is a process with countless variants and
constraints which have led to a multitude of studies in recent years
due to its importance. The approaches in the literature could be
classified, among other ways, according to the waste type that is
treated. Some of them are: residential waste commonly known
as garbage
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">(Garvin et al., 2011)</xref>
        , industrial waste where
customers/containers are more dispersed and the amount of waste
is higher
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">(Rabbani et al., 2018)</xref>
        , recyclable waste
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">(Dat et al.,
2012)</xref>
        increasingly important for our society, where the
collection frequency is lower than organic waste and hazardous
waste where the probability of harm and costs are both
minimized
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">(Rabbani et al., 2018)</xref>
        .
      </p>
      <p>
        In municipal solid waste collection (
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">Beliën et al., 2014</xref>
        ), the
authorities need global studies to quantify the waste generated
in a period of time to be able to manage it. For example,
waste generation forecasting for the inhabitants of Xiamen City
(China) was studied by
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">(Xu et al., 2013)</xref>
        . The main di erence
with our approach is the granularity of the object under study.
They predict the amount of waste produced in the whole city, in
contrast, we generate predictions for every single container in a
city.
      </p>
      <p>
        This supposes a considerable increase in the complexity of
the problem that is to be solved, because it is necessary to
consider multiple aspects such as the location, the customs of the
citizens, the population density of the area, etc. Along the same
research lines, the impact of the intervention of local authorities
on waste collection has also been studied
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">(Cole et al., 2014)</xref>
        ,
with this being relevant in the medium-long term.
      </p>
      <p>
        Regarding the location where the collection takes place, there
exist multiple variants of the problem. There are communal
collections where the local authority identifies a place shared
by the community
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">(Tung and Pinnoi, 2000)</xref>
        , in most cases a
local waste facility for recycling. On the other side, we found
the kerbside collection
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">(Sniezek and Bodin, 2006)</xref>
        where the
household waste is collected from individual small containers
located near each house. The intermediate case studied here
is the collection of containers which serve several streets and
blocks of flats
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">(Sakti et al., 2018)</xref>
        .
      </p>
      <p>
        In medium/large cities, the number of containers is in the
range of hundreds or even thousands, therefore the use of
advanced computational methods are required to find an
optimal solution. In the past, exact methods were used to solve
this problem like Branch and Bound, based on mathematical
programming
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">(Arribas et al., 2010)</xref>
        . However the execution
time tends to increase exponentially with the number of
containers, so the use of hybrid methods like matheuristics
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13 ref14 ref15">Gruler
et al. (2017</xref>
        a) and bioinspired methods is recommended.
Although some metaheuristics have already been explored in
the literature such as Ant Colony optimization, Genetic
Algorithms
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">(Buenrostro-Delgado et al., 2015)</xref>
        , Greedy Randomized
      </p>
      <sec id="sec-2-1">
        <title>Adaptive Search Procedure Gruler et al. (2017b), or Variable</title>
        <p>
          Neighborhood Search
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13 ref14 ref15">Gruler et al. (2017</xref>
          c). There is still room
for improvement when one is dealing with the waste collection
problem at the fine granularity we address it in our approach,
that is, analyzing each of every single container.
        </p>
        <p>
          The waste collection process implies a large quantity of
stakeholders like authorities, citizens, the company in charge of
the collection service and the company workers. Depending on
the stakeholder, the objectives to optimize are di erent. Some
examples of optimization goals are the number of vehicles for
the service
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">(Ombuki-Berman et al., 2007)</xref>
          , the service total
cost
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">(Arribas et al., 2010)</xref>
          , the environmental impact
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1 ref29">(Tavares
et al., 2009)</xref>
          , the required sta for the service
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">(Hansmann and
Zimmermann, 2009)</xref>
          , the collection route length
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">(Ustundag and
Cevikcan, 2008)</xref>
          , and the total time of the waste collection
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">(Arribas et al., 2010)</xref>
          . Our approach considers several objectives
at a time, finding solutions which minimize the number of
vehicles needed, the total cost, the route length, and the
environmental impact.
        </p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>3. Problem Description</title>
      <p>Waste collection management is a global problem that a ects
most cities around the world. In fact, this problem falls within
the initiative of Horizon 2020 and Smart City for innovation
and research, promoted by the European Union. The reduction
of energy consumption and the responsible use of resources has
become key to combat the rigors of the economic crisis.
Specifically, one of the objectives of the Smart City initiative is to
reduce the emission of greenhouse gases, use sustainable
resources, and e ciently manage energy sources. We are
therefore dealing with a problem of general interest in this article.
We focus on some of the aspects discussed in Section 2.
Specifically, we study recyclable waste, we use fine grain predictions
for every single container, we manage hundreds of containers,
and we use an evolutionary algorithm as resolution technique.</p>
      <p>The problem consists of planning how the waste collection
will take place in a determined area. The objective is to define
optimal collection routes for the available trucks whose
capacity cannot be exceeded. An optimal collection route is an
ordered list of collection places to visit that minimizes the total
distance traveled by all the trucks involved.</p>
      <p>Since the number of containers is great for all of them to be
collected every day and it is not a cost-e ective strategy, the
containers must be visited at a more appropriate time (ideally
when their filling level is close to 100%). In addition, routes are
constrained by the trucks’ capacities, that may di er. Moreover,
there exist constraints which a ect specific containers that must
be collected by a small truck (with less capacity) due to space
restrictions. Route duration is determined by the travel time
between containers and the time to empty them.</p>
      <p>
        Generally, there are some di culties in estimating the
distances and duration of trips between containers due to tra c
conditions. Most approaches
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20 ref30">(Nuortio et al., 2006, Teixeira
et al., 2004)</xref>
        only use the distance as a criterion for
generating the cost matrix. They calculate the shortest paths between
pairs of waste containers using the Dijkstra algorithm
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">(Dijkstra,
1959)</xref>
        . In contrast, we have opted to calculate the estimated
distance and duration between pairs of containers using the Google
Maps Api v3. By doing so, we obtain a more accurate value for
travel distance and duration taking into account tra c
regulations and conditions.
      </p>
      <p>The quantity deposited daily in each container is unknown, it
depends on multiple factors such as the number of citizens
sharing a container, the seasonality and lifestyle. In other papers,
the authors assume the quantity deposited in the containers is
constant every day, however, BIN-CT treats each container as a
di erent entity that can change daily. As the previous fill levels
of the containers are available, the software system forecasts
future fill levels based on historical data. This information will
help determine which containers must be collected in the next
shift. The predictions generation is really complex, since we
need to model the behavior of the population that deposits its
waste in a specific container.</p>
      <p>Overall, the complexity of this problem can be derived from
the number of restrictions that can be applied to the model, so
that the more restrictions applied, the more realistic the solution
found and the larger its computational complexity. The
constraints we take into account are highly diverse. With respect to
the trucks, we can restrict the capacity of each vehicle
individually, the number of them and the ability to collect containers
in narrow streets. The quality of service defined by the waste
management company (imposed by the local authorities in the
contract with the company) could be seen as a soft constraint. In
this paper the company establishes that all the containers with a
filling estimation greater than 80% must be collected. In
summary, we enumerate the constraints considered here:</p>
      <sec id="sec-3-1">
        <title>Containers:</title>
        <p>– Variable number of containers
– Di erent demands
– Di erent locations
– Custom unloading time</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-2">
        <title>Vehicles:</title>
        <p>– Only specific trucks can unload a particular container
– Variable number of vehicles
– Di erent loading capacities
– Ability to unload specific containers (narrow streets)
– Custom cost based on distance traveled</p>
        <p>
          The vehicle routing problem is well known to be NP-hard
and the waste collection problem described here is basically a
VRP with several constraints, so it is even harder to solve.
Furthermore, a realistic instance involving 50 or more containers
and several vehicles, means thousands of decision variables and
constraints
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">Varone et al. (2014)</xref>
          . Therefore the use of heuristics
to obtain quasi-optimal solutions in a moderate time is
recommended. In this paper, we use evolutionary algorithms for this
purpose.
        </p>
        <sec id="sec-3-2-1">
          <title>3.1. Problem Formulation</title>
          <p>The underlying VRP in the waste collection problem is a
combinatorial problem whose ground set is the edges of a graph
G(C; A). The notation used for this problem formulation is as
follows:</p>
          <p>C = fc0; c1; : : : ; cn; cn+1g is a container set, where a
depot (0 denotes the depot) is located at c0 and cn+1, and
C0 = Cn fc0; cn+1g is the set of n containers.</p>
          <p>A = n(ci; c j)jci; c j 2 C; i , jo is a directed arc set.</p>
          <p>D is a matrix of non-negative distances (meters) di j
between containers ci and c j.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-3">
        <title>Ri is the route for vehicle i.</title>
        <p>Vi is the vehicle i which has a maximum capacity vi.
v is the number of vehicles. One route is assigned to each
vehicle.
s is a binary vector, which indicates if Vi has the size to
access the location of certain containers(e.g. those located
in the city center).
w is a binary vector, which indicates if the container ci
must be collected by a vehicle Vi | si = 1 .</p>
        <p>In a real city the distance between a container i and j could
be di erent due to tra c regulations, therefore when 9i; j Di j ,
D ji the problem is said to be asymmetric.</p>
        <p>Each vertex ci in C0 has an associated quantity qi of waste to
be loaded by a vehicle. The VRP thus consists in determining
a set of v vehicle routes of minimal total cost, starting and
ending at a depot, such that the maximum waste is collected and
a container is visited at most once. Note that each vehicle has
an associated maximum load capacity vi which can not be
exceeded, i.e., the total quantity of waste of all containers serviced
on a route Ri must not exceed the vehicle capacity vi.</p>
        <p>A feasible solution is composed of a set of routes
R1; : : : ; Ri; : : : ; Rv where Ri is the route for the vehicle i and
a permutation i of Ri S 0 (0 denotes the depot) specifying the
order of the containers on route i. In addition, each route has to
fulfill the following constraint related to the size of the
containers: if 9 c j 2 Ri such that w j = 1 (e.g. the container is in the
city center), then si = 1 (the vehicle has the size to reach those
containers).</p>
        <p>Additionally, we consider a service time i (time needed to
load the container), required by a vehicle to load the quantity qi
at container ci. In this context, the time duration i to collect c j
is the service time i plus the travel time t ji. Note that in this
approach i (costs associated with the travel time and service
time) are used to report an estimation of the duration of the
routes.</p>
        <p>The cost of a given route (Ri = fc0; c1; : : : ; cv+1g), where
ci 2 C and c0 = vc+1 = 0 (0 denotes the depot), is given by
C(Ri) =</p>
        <p>v
X D(ci; ci+1)
i=0
FitnessS =</p>
        <p>v
X C(Ri) + p nac
i=1</p>
        <p>Finally, the fitness for the problem solution S is given by:
where p is a penalty value and nac is the number of unassigned
containers (due to vehicles’ maximum capacity constraint). In
this paper we set p = 500, a high enough value for this instance.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-4">
      <title>4. Our Proposal: BIN-CT Predictive System</title>
      <p>(1)
(2)
T is matrix of non-negative duration (seconds) ti j between
containers ci and c j.</p>
      <p>The BIN-CT predictive system has been designed to improve
municipal waste collection planning. Our software system is
a combination of two main algorithms, one for predicting the
filling levels of the containers and one for computing the best
routes to visit them. These algorithms are encoded into a
software package that o ers a Graphical User Interface (GUI) so
that a manager in the recycling company can make informed
decisions and take action, like giving daily routes to truck drivers
to follow or pursuing new o ine studies like analyzing the
evolution in time of the filling level of the containers.</p>
      <p>To deal with the complexity of the global problem, we
address it in four sequential phases. In the first phase, the travel
distances and duration for all pairs of containers are computed
to give more realism to the solution. Then, in the second phase,
the fill levels are estimated and the containers which are not
going to be part of the routes for the next service are discarded.
In the third phase the routes are generated, minimizing the
total cost, and in the last phase we show the best solution in a
web browser. Therefore, we divided the tool into four di erent
modules which can be seen in Figure 2.</p>
      <p>In this section we detail the main features of our software,
as well as the solution quality it achieves when solving an
instance of the solid waste collection problem described here.
The BIN-CT predictive system comprises four software
modules: A Data Management module, Intelligent Decision
module, Routes Generation module and Visualization module.</p>
      <sec id="sec-4-1">
        <title>4.1. Data Management Module</title>
        <p>All information for the execution of the software that comes
from the waste management company, which undertakes the
collection, can be loaded from a database. The use of a database
is desirable due to the amount of information needed to solve</p>
        <sec id="sec-4-1-1">
          <title>Entity</title>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-4-1-2">
          <title>Containers</title>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-4-1-3">
          <title>Historical Data</title>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-4-1-4">
          <title>Vehicles</title>
          <p>the problem. The main entities (input and output data) used
in our system are shown in Figure 3. Additionally, we list the
input data needed to run BIN-CT e ectively in Table 1.</p>
          <p>The main entity is Containers. We store the identification
of the container, information about the location such as
coordinates and addresses, the maximum capacity of the container,
how long it takes to collect the container, the type of waste
(glass, paper,...), the type of the truck needed to collect the
container (e.g., small truck in narrow central streets) and whether it
has a sensor or not to measure the fill-level.</p>
          <p>The container is related to the historical filling data entity
where we store the filling data of each container. It is also
related to the Costs entity where we store the distance and
estimated duration of the trip between containers. This information
is extracted with Google Maps Api v3 and is used to solve the
underlying VRP. The generation of the duration and distance
matrix is essential to generate a realistic solution.</p>
          <p>The table Forecasts stores the predictions generated by the
machine-learning algorithms that are used to estimate which
containers will be collected in the next service. To undertake a
service, the company has vehicles that have di erent sizes and
loading capacities, which we must consider as constraints. A
smaller truck has less loading capacity; thus it usually collects
fewer containers.</p>
          <p>Finally, once the execution of the route optimization
algorithm has finished, we store the best solution in the database for
visualization purposes. The solution of the whole problem is an
ordered list of containers that must be visited by each vehicle.
This information is stored in the entities Solution and Tasks.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-4-2">
        <title>4.2. Intelligent Decisions Module</title>
        <p>
          The fundamental characteristic of our software is the ability
to predict the daily waste contribution for each of the containers
that are part of the analyzed set. We have carried out an
individualized mathematical modeling of each container using Weka’s
machine learning library
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">(Frank et al., 2016)</xref>
          . Specifically we
have used the time series analysis, which is the process of
using statistical techniques to model and explain a time-dependent
series of data points. Therefore, time-series forecasting is the
process of using a model to generate predictions (forecasts) for
future events based on known past events, like the fill-level of
each container. The time-series forecasting algorithms enable
the tool to generate filling predictions for those containers not
monitored with sensors.
        </p>
        <p>In this module we have also defined the inclusion/exclusion
criteria used to make decisions about the containers that will be
collected using the generated routes. The inclusion/excursion
criteria can be defined according to container capacity, forecasts
made, and real readings of the sensors, if possible. In addition,
given a set of containers and a criterion, we have the possibility
of forcing the inclusion of some containers with higher priority
on the routes, and some may be excluded due to the defined
criteria and constraints.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-4-3">
        <title>4.3. Routes Generation Module</title>
        <p>
          This module has, as its main functionality, the generation of
optimal routes for the waste collection. Given a set of
containers, we use an evolutionary algorithm EA(1+1) based on
the principle of ruin and recreation
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">(Schrimpf et al., 2000)</xref>
          that
allows us to generate e cient collection routes, taking into
account the distance and the driving time between them.
        </p>
        <p>In general, all the containers have the same capacity, but as
time goes on, city managers buy new containers with
potentially new, di erent capacities. Our software considers
containers of di erent sizes and, therefore, di erent capacities. The
capacity of each one is managed individually, and this allows us
to estimate the total waste that the vehicle will collect, since we
cannot exceed the load limit. In addition, vehicle fleets are not
only made up of identical vehicles, but vehicle fleets are
heterogeneous, so vehicles are also considered individually. For
example, we can assign a larger number of containers to
vehicles with higher capacity.</p>
        <p>Sometimes there are special cases where the compatibility
between container and vehicle has to be taken into account.
This is the case when a container has to be picked up by a small
vehicle. Our software allows us to take this restriction into
account in order to generate valid routes. In addition, this feature
can also influence the container collection time, which is the
time it takes to the driver to pick up the container once it is in
front of it. This input time is assigned depending on the location
or characteristics of the container to be collected. This
characteristic has a beneficial e ect on the fact that the total estimated
collection time is more realistic.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-4-4">
        <title>4.3.1. Algorithm</title>
        <p>
          The evolutionary algorithm EA(1+1) used to solve the
routing problem is based on the ruin and recreate principle. It is
a large neighborhood search that combines elements of
simulated annealing and threshold-accepting algorithms. This
approach is suitable for complex problems that have many
constraints
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19 ref26">(Schrimpf et al., 2000, Misevicius, 2003)</xref>
          . It is an
allpurpose metaheuristic that can be used to solve a number of
classical VRP types and basic search strategies can be easily
varied to small and large movements according to the
complexity of the problem. The pseudocode of the algorithm is shown
in Algorithm 1.
        </p>
        <sec id="sec-4-4-1">
          <title>Algorithm 1 Pseudocode of the algorithm.</title>
          <p>Inputs: Set of containers (location, fill-level, predictions), set
of vehicles, distance matrix, duration matrix, deposit location
Output: Set of ordered lists of containers
1: bestSolution randomSolution()
2: while evals &lt; totalEvals do
3: initialSolution randomSolution()
4: removedTasks ruin(initialSolution)
5: newSolution reCreation(removedTask)
6: evaluate(newSolution)
7: if (newSolution&lt;bestSolution) then
8: bestSolution newSolution
9: end if
10: end while
11: return bestSolution</p>
          <p>The algorithm starts with a random initial solution. It
divides parts of the solution leading to a set of tasks (collecting a
container) that are not going to be assigned to a vehicle and a
partial solution containing all other tasks. This process is called
ruin the solution because we extract some tasks from the
solution. Based on the partial solution, the algorithm reintroduces
the tasks extracted leading to a new solution. Hence, this is the
recreation process. If the new solution has more quality than
the best-so-far solution, it is accepted as the new best solution.
These steps are repeated until the algorithm reaches a number
of iterations.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-4-5">
        <title>4.4. Visualization Module</title>
        <p>The solutions are shown in an HTML navigable map. The
software generates solutions for one or more days, and these
can be viewed in a web browser. In Figure 4 we show the
interface of the web application, which can also be viewed online
at http://mallba3.lcc.uma.es/binct/. The main part shows a
solution obtained for two vehicles: one red route and another black
route, with two di erent trucks. In addition, we can observe the
containers marked in red, which will be those whose prediction
indicates a percentage of filling higher than 80%.</p>
        <p>The solutions can be accessed from any mobile device and
the user interface adapts itself to the platform on the fly. This
feature is especially desirable when the trucks’ drivers have any
doubts regarding the route they should follow.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-5">
      <title>5. Experiments</title>
      <p>In this paper we carry out two di erent experiments. First,
we focus on the predictions, which is the most innovative part
of our system. They will allow us to achieve the greatest
savings in the operation of our waste collection service. This first
experiment consists in the comparison of three di erent
algorithms to generate predictions.</p>
      <p>The second experiment is the generation of routes for a
working day, starting from the real state that the containers had, so
that, they have di erent filling states. These fill levels are
complemented by the predictions for the next day. We compare our
solution with the real solution provided by the company’s
human experts for that exact day (what really happened that day).
In this way, we try to show that our approach is realistic, and
therefore our solutions are too. As quality measures we analyze
the distance, duration, and amount of waste collected using the
generated routes. As a performance measure we report the time
required to run the algorithm. We completed 30 independent
runs in order to provide a fair value for the runtime. Finally,
the experiments were run on a machine with Intel Core i7-3770
processor at 3.40 GHz and 16 GB memory.</p>
      <sec id="sec-5-1">
        <title>5.1. Case of Study</title>
        <p>In this article we illustrate the behavior of BIN-CT with a real
case study of an Andalusian city (Spain), where we highlight
the benefits of our approach, showing it to also be e ective and
realistic. Our case study considers 217 paper containers from
the metropolitan area of the city. The choice of an instance of
recycling waste is more attractive than an organic waste
collection. In this sense, we show the quality of our approach because
most paper containers do not need to be emptied every day like
organic waste ones, so they have a high variability in collection
frequency. The problem instance parameters used in the case
study are shown in Table 2.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-2">
        <title>5.2. Experiment 1: Comparison of Time Series Algorithms</title>
        <p>
          This experiment is intended to carry out a comparison
between three time-series algorithms used to forecast the
filllevel for all containers. The algorithms used in this
comparison are: Linear Regression
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">(Su et al., 2012)</xref>
          , Gaussian
processes
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">(Mackay, 1998)</xref>
          and Support Vector Machine for
regression (SMOreg)
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">(Rivas-Perea, 2013)</xref>
          . We briefly describe the
techniques on which the algorithms are based:
        </p>
        <p>Linear regression works by estimating coe cients for a
line that best fits the training data. It is a good idea to
evaluate linear regression on a problem as a baseline, before
moving onto more complex algorithms.</p>
        <p>Gaussian process is a collection of random variables, any
finite number of which have a joint Gaussian distribution.
A Gaussian process is completely specified by a mean
function and a positive definite covariance function.
SMOreg works by finding a line of best fit that minimizes
the error of a cost function. This is done using an
optimization process that only considers those data instances
in the training dataset that are closest to the line with the
minimum cost.</p>
        <p>In this experiment we use the fill-level of all 217 containers
in 11 months. The data is obtained by the truck driver when the
container is unloaded. If the container is not visited, then there
is no datum for that specific day. Thus, the system must deduce
what happened on those days for which we do not have data.</p>
        <p>In order to alleviate this issue, we have performed a
preprocessing of the data that has allowed us to obtain the
estimated daily load increase of the containers. From the processed
data, we have generated the daily predictions for the following
month using the three forecasting algorithms.</p>
        <p>The results indicate that the learning algorithm based on
Gaussian processes is the best algorithm in our comparison,
obtaining an average of just 3.83% mean absolute error in the
filling predictions of next month. Regarding the other
techniques, the algorithm based on linear regression has an
average of 7.41% mean absolute error and the SMOreg algorithm
has 9.52%. After performing the Kruskal-Wallis statistical test
(with Bonferroni correction to compare more than two samples)
with 95% confidence, we can state that there are significant
differences between the results of the algorithm based on Gaussian
processes with the other two algorithms of the comparison.</p>
        <p>As the main conclusion of the first experiment, we can infer
that the estimation provided by the best algorithm is more than
acceptable, with less than 4% mean absolute error. Note that a
container is scheduled for the next collection service when the
filling estimation is greater than 80%, so the error is so
negligible as to not a ect the decision to collect a container. After
analyzing these results, we decided to use the algorithm based
on Gaussian processes for the second experiment.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-3">
        <title>5.3. Experiment 2: The Daily Use of the System</title>
        <p>In the second experiment, we want to illustrate the general
behavior of the system considering all the parameters specified
in Table 2. In this experiment we generate routes for the first
working day of the twelfth month starting from the real state
of the containers and then we compare our solution with the
real solution implemented that day. Once our system has given
the predictions for the following day, we obtain the estimated
fill-level for all containers. Next, BIN-CT chooses the subset
of containers that fulfills the following inclusion/exclusion
criteria. Those containers with a fill-level higher than 50 % are
considered optional, while those with a filling greater than 80
% are marked for mandatory collection.The application of this
criterion to the set of 217 containers results in a subset of 77
containers to be picked up by two vehicles (the smallest is able
to pick up the nine containers that cannot be collected by the
big truck).</p>
        <p>In Table 3 we show the containers collected, the duration and
distance of the routes, and the load of the trucks in the experts
solution and the solution provided by BIN-CT. In addition, we
show the totals of the measures for both vehicles and the
average per container. After the execution of the route
generation algorithm, we obtain two di erent routes: the biggest truck
should pick up 41 containers and the smallest truck should visit
33 containers. Therefore, our solution is able to schedule most
of the containers with only 3 containers not scheduled for the
next service due to truck capacity constraints.</p>
        <p>The system provides very accurate information on the
duration of the routes, the duration of the four routes can be seen in
the fourth column in Table 3. On the one hand, the route of the
small truck has an estimated duration of 3 hours, 39 minutes
and 51 seconds to collect a total of 33 containers. On the other
hand, the route of the big truck will last 3 hours, 52 minutes
and 40 seconds to collect a total of 41 containers. However, if
we take a look at the distance, the small truck’s route is 32.4
km compared with just 25.2 km of the other route. Therefore,
it seems that the constraint of picking up those 9 containers,
which cannot be collected by the big truck, is a detrimental to
the small truck’s route. Regarding the trucks load, the amount
of waste collected is proportional to each truck’s size.</p>
        <p>Let us compare the experts solution with our solution. First
of all, we analyze how many containers, which are also in the
expert’s solution, were selected by BIN-CT. The result is that
66% of the experts’ solution’s containers are also collected in
the solution provided by BIN-CT. This means that using static
plans, sometimes they collect containers that are below 50%
according to our estimations. Actually, around 20% of the
containers (12 units) of the studied day had less than 50% fill-level.
Our system is therefore unique in detecting them and saving
costs in the planning.</p>
        <p>The routes provided by BIN-CT are able to pick up more
containers, in less time per container, traveling fewer kilometers
and taking more advantage of the load capacity of the trucks.
We must highlight the di erence in distance traveled. We would
save 20% of the distance traveled in comparison with the real
solution even though our routes took 19 minutes and 55
seconds more than the real ones. If we used the average distance
to collect a container and multiply that by the 62 containers
of the real solution, then the estimated distance traveled would
be 48,333 meters, which means we would have 33.2% shorter
routes than the routes used by the company. The algorithm runs
with the default parameters and a stop criterion of 10,000
iterations. The median runtime was 27,350 milliseconds that is less
than half a minute, so the algorithm is quite fast. Moreover, if
we increase the iteration budget, potentially we would obtain
even better results.</p>
        <p>After specialized sta from the company, who gave us the
data for the case of study, validated the solutions generated by
BIN-CT, we can conclude that our system generates realistic
solutions and reproduces with enough reliability, what happens
in reality. In addition, the use of the fill predictions discarded
140 containers not included as nodes to visit in the generation of
routes process. Actually, all containers (except one) which were
not included in our routes but included in the real ones, were
discarded based on the forecasting and not because of truck
capacity constraints. This fact means that with high probability
we have saved unnecessary visits to semi-empty containers that
are part of a predefined static route for the day analyzed.
Therefore using BIN-CT implies a reduction in both the cost of the
routes and the harmful emissions thrown by the trucks.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-6">
      <title>6. Conclusions and Future Work</title>
      <p>Traditional solid waste management is usually based on
previous experience rather than data. Currently the waste
collection plans are static with a predetermined number of visits
per week and designed manually, which implies a slow
adaptation to any change in normal conditions. In this paper we
have proposed BIN-CT, an intelligent predictive software
system designed to use knowledge extracted from historical data
and technology that is part of the state-of-the-art in urban
sustainability research. We are convinced that our intelligent
system will help to improve the quality of life of the city where it
is implemented. The reduction of costs and the e cient
treatment of the waste generated will constitute a way to achieve
sustainability in the city.</p>
      <p>Our aim is to reduce the costs of the waste collection service,
while increasing the quality of service for the citizen. Our
software suggests the collection of containers above 80 % and thus
avoids the annoying overflows of containers. Through the study
case that we have analyzed in this article, we prove that the
solutions generated are realistic. At the same time, they are more
e cient because the solutions prevent trips to semi-empty
containers and the generated routes are 33.2% shorter than those
used by the company. Moreover, after the comparison of three
di erent algorithms, we used the best which generates
predictions with just a 3.83% mean absolute error. This fact indicates
that the forecasting performed is fairly reliable for the
calculations we need to make in our system.</p>
      <p>BIN-CT has a direct application for waste management
companies, both in Spanish cities and elsewhere in the world.
This non-commercial software system, based on computational
learning algorithms, does not require a large investment in
infrastructure, which is why it is highly attractive to companies.
There is also an interesting scientific side (use of time series,
predictions, e cient algorithms, . . . ) that companies may be
interested in, which could make the leap in quality and
distinction that is sought after in a market as competitive as the current
one.</p>
      <p>As for future work, we highlight the possible integration of
an indeterminate number of sensors, in a larger cyber-physical
system, to measure the amount of waste in the containers. The
way the system is built facilitates an easy integration of sensors.
The use of sensors makes it possible to change a route in real
time by adding or removing containers. Fortunately, this
valuable feature could save more unnecessary trips to containers,
while at the same time preventing possible overflows of
containers.</p>
      <p>
        Regarding the algorithms for the generation of predictions,
here we have studied some techniques for time-series prediction
based on regression. However, recently the recurring neural
network technique has emerged as a good method for the
generation of time-series predictions
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17 ref5">(LeCun et al., 2015, Camero
et al., 2018)</xref>
        . We plan to improve the fill-level predictions by
using an algorithm based on recurring neural networks.
      </p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-7">
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>This research has been partially funded by the Spanish
Ministry of Science and Innovation and FEDER under
contracts RTC-2017-6714-5 and TIN2017-88213-R and the
network of smart cities CI-RTI (TIN2016-81766-REDT). The
CELTIC project C2017/2-2 under contracts #8.06/5.47.4997 y
#8.06/5.47.4996. J. Ferrer thanks University of Málaga for his
postdoc fellowship.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Al-Salem</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>S. M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Lettieri</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Baeyens</surname>
          </string-name>
          , J., oct
          <year>2009</year>
          .
          <article-title>Recycling and recovery routes of plastic solid waste (PSW): A review</article-title>
          .
          <source>Waste Management</source>
          <volume>29</volume>
          (
          <issue>10</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>2625</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>2643</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Arribas</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>C. A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Blazquez</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>C. A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Lamas</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , apr
          <year>2010</year>
          .
          <article-title>Urban solid waste collection system using mathematical modelling and tools of geographic information systems</article-title>
          .
          <source>Waste Management &amp; Research</source>
          <volume>28</volume>
          (
          <issue>4</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>355</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>363</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Beliën</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>De Boeck</surname>
          </string-name>
          , L.,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Van Ackere</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , feb
          <year>2014</year>
          .
          <article-title>Municipal Solid Waste Collection and Management Problems: A Literature Review</article-title>
          .
          <source>Transportation Science</source>
          <volume>48</volume>
          (
          <issue>1</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>78</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>102</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Buenrostro-Delgado</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>O.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Ortega-Rodriguez</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J. M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Clemitshaw</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>K. C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>González-Razo</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Hernández-Paniagua</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>I. Y.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>2015</year>
          .
          <article-title>Use of genetic algorithms to improve the solid waste collection service in an urban area</article-title>
          . Waste management (New York, N.Y.)
          <volume>41</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>20</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Camero</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Toutouh</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Stolfi</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>D. H.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Alba</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>2018</year>
          .
          <article-title>Evolutionary Deep Learning for Car Park Occupancy Prediction in Smart Cities</article-title>
          .
          <source>In: Learning and Intelligent OptimizatioN Conference LION.</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cole</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Quddus</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Wheatley</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Osmani</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Kay</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , feb
          <year>2014</year>
          .
          <article-title>The impact of Local Authorities' interventions on household waste collection: a case study approach using time series modelling</article-title>
          . Waste management (New York, N.Y.)
          <volume>34</volume>
          (
          <issue>2</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>266</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>72</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Dantzig</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>G. B.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Ramser</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J. H.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>1959</year>
          .
          <article-title>The Truck Dispatching Problem</article-title>
          .
          <source>Management Science</source>
          <volume>6</volume>
          (
          <issue>1</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>80</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>91</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Dat</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>L. Q.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Truc Linh</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>D. T.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Chou</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>S. Y.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>V. F.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>2012</year>
          .
          <article-title>Optimizing reverse logistic costs for recycling end-of-life electrical and electronic products</article-title>
          .
          <source>Expert Systems with Applications</source>
          <volume>39</volume>
          (
          <issue>7</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>6380</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>6387</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Dijkstra</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>E. W.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>1959</year>
          .
          <article-title>A note on two problems in connexion with graphs</article-title>
          .
          <source>Numerische Mathematik</source>
          <volume>1</volume>
          (
          <issue>1</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>269</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>271</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Frank</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Hall</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Witten</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>I. H.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>2016</year>
          . The WEKA Workbench.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Garvin</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>B. J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Cohen,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
            ,
            <surname>Dwyer</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>M. B.</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>2011</year>
          .
          <article-title>Evaluating improvements to a meta-heuristic search for constrained interaction testing</article-title>
          .
          <source>Empirical Software Engineering</source>
          <volume>16</volume>
          (
          <issue>1</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>61</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>102</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Ghisellini</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cialani</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Ulgiati</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>2016</year>
          .
          <article-title>A review on circular economy: The expected transition to a balanced interplay of environmental and economic systems</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Cleaner Production</source>
          <volume>114</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>11</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>32</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Gruler</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Fikar</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Juan</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Hirsch</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Contreras-Bolton</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , feb 2017a.
          <article-title>Supporting multi-depot and stochastic waste collection management in clustered urban areas via simulation-optimization</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Simulation</source>
          <volume>11</volume>
          (
          <issue>1</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>11</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>19</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Gruler</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Fikar</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Juan</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Hirsch</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Contreras-Bolton</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , feb 2017b.
          <article-title>Supporting multi-depot and stochastic waste collection management in clustered urban areas via simulation-optimization</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Simulation</source>
          <volume>11</volume>
          (
          <issue>1</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>11</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>19</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Gruler</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Fikar</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Juan</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Hirsch</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Contreras-Bolton</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , feb 2017c.
          <article-title>Supporting multi-depot and stochastic waste collection management in clustered urban areas via simulation-optimization</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Simulation</source>
          <volume>11</volume>
          (
          <issue>1</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>11</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>19</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Hansmann</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>R. S.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Zimmermann</surname>
          </string-name>
          , U. T.,
          <year>2009</year>
          .
          <article-title>Integrated Vehicle Routing and Crew Scheduling ( IVRCS</article-title>
          ) in
          <source>Waste Management Part I. Dagstuhl Seminar Proceedings 09261 Models and Algorithms for Optimization in Logistics</source>
          , 1-
          <fpage>8</fpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>LeCun</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>Y. A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Bengio</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Hinton</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>G. E.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>2015</year>
          .
          <article-title>Deep learning</article-title>
          .
          <source>Nature</source>
          <volume>521</volume>
          (
          <issue>7553</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>436</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>444</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Mackay</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>D. J. C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>1998</year>
          .
          <article-title>Introduction to Gaussian processes</article-title>
          .
          <source>Neural Networks and Machine Learning</source>
          <volume>168</volume>
          (
          <year>1996</year>
          ),
          <fpage>133</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>165</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Misevicius</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>2003</year>
          .
          <article-title>Genetic algorithm hybridized with ruin and recreate procedure: Application to the quadratic assignment problem</article-title>
          .
          <source>In: KnowledgeBased Systems</source>
          . Vol.
          <volume>16</volume>
          . pp.
          <fpage>261</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>268</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Nuortio</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Kytöjoki</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Niska</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Bräysy</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>O.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>2006</year>
          .
          <article-title>Improved route planning and scheduling of waste collection and transport</article-title>
          .
          <source>Expert Systems with Applications</source>
          <volume>30</volume>
          (
          <issue>2</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>223</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>232</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Ombuki-Berman</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>B. M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Runka</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Hanshar</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>F. T.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>2007</year>
          .
          <article-title>Waste collection vehicle routing problem with time windows using multi-objective genetic algorithms</article-title>
          .
          <source>Proceedings of the Third IASTED International Conference on Computational Intelligence</source>
          ,
          <fpage>91</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>97</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Rabbani</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Heidari</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Farrokhi-Asl</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Rahimi</surname>
          </string-name>
          , N., jan
          <year>2018</year>
          .
          <article-title>Using metaheuristic algorithms to solve a multi-objective industrial hazardous waste location-routing problem considering incompatible waste types</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Cleaner Production</source>
          <volume>170</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>227</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>241</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Rivas-Perea</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>2013</year>
          .
          <article-title>Support Vector Machines for Regression: A Succinct Review of Large-Scale and Linear Programming Formulations</article-title>
          .
          <source>International Journal of Intelligence Science</source>
          <volume>03</volume>
          (
          <issue>01</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>5</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>14</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref24">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Sakti</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>V. F.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Sopha</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>B. M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>2018</year>
          .
          <article-title>Heterogeneous Fleet Location Routing Problem for Waste Management: A Case Study of Yogyakarta, Indonesia</article-title>
          . In: International Conference in Management Science and
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Decision</given-names>
            <surname>Making</surname>
          </string-name>
          . pp.
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>11</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref25">
        <mixed-citation>URL https://repository.ugm.ac.id/274607/1/2018{_}ICSDM. pdf</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref26">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Schrimpf</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Schneider</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Stamm-Wilbrandt</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Dueck</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>2000</year>
          .
          <article-title>Record Breaking Optimization Results Using the Ruin and Recreate Principle</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Computational Physics</source>
          <volume>159</volume>
          (
          <issue>2</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>139</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>171</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref27">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Sniezek</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Bodin</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , apr
          <year>2006</year>
          .
          <article-title>Using mixed integer programming for solving the capacitated arc routing problem with vehicle/site dependencies with an application to the routing of residential sanitation collection vehicles</article-title>
          .
          <source>Annals of Operations Research</source>
          <volume>144</volume>
          (
          <issue>1</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>33</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>58</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref28">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Su</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Yan</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tsai</surname>
          </string-name>
          , C.-L.,
          <year>2012</year>
          .
          <article-title>Linear regression</article-title>
          .
          <source>Wiley Interdisciplinary Reviews: Computational Statistics</source>
          <volume>4</volume>
          (
          <issue>3</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>275</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>294</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref29">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tavares</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Zsigraiova</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Semiao</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>V.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Carvalho</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , mar
          <year>2009</year>
          .
          <article-title>Optimisation of MSW collection routes for minimum fuel consumption using 3D GIS modelling</article-title>
          .
          <source>Waste Management</source>
          <volume>29</volume>
          (
          <issue>3</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>1176</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1185</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref30">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Teixeira</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Antunes</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A. P.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , de Sousa,
          <string-name>
            <surname>J. P.</surname>
          </string-name>
          , nov
          <year>2004</year>
          .
          <article-title>Recyclable waste collection planning--a case study</article-title>
          .
          <source>European Journal of Operational Research</source>
          <volume>158</volume>
          (
          <issue>3</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>543</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>554</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref31">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tukker</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>2015</year>
          .
          <article-title>Product services for a resource-e cient and circular economy - A review</article-title>
          .
          <source>Journal of Cleaner Production</source>
          <volume>97</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>76</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>91</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref32">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tung</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>D. V.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Pinnoi</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>2000</year>
          .
          <article-title>Vehicle routing-scheduling for waste collection in Hanoi</article-title>
          .
          <source>European Journal of Operational Research</source>
          <volume>125</volume>
          (
          <issue>3</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>449</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>468</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref33">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Ustundag</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cevikcan</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>2008</year>
          .
          <article-title>Vehicle Route Optimization for Rfid Integrated Waste Collection System</article-title>
          .
          <source>International Journal of Information Technology &amp; Decision Making</source>
          <volume>07</volume>
          (
          <issue>04</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>611</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>625</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref34">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Varone</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Markov</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>I.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Bierlaire</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>2014</year>
          .
          <article-title>Vehicle Routing for a Complex Waste Collection Problem Iliya Markov, Ecole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne Vehicle Routing for a Complex Waste Collection Problem</article-title>
          .
          <source>Tech. rep.</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref35">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Gao</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cui</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Liu,
          <string-name>
            <surname>C.</surname>
          </string-name>
          , jun
          <year>2013</year>
          .
          <article-title>A hybrid procedure for MSW generation forecasting at multiple time scales in Xiamen City, China</article-title>
          . Waste management (New York, N.Y.)
          <volume>33</volume>
          (
          <issue>6</issue>
          ),
          <fpage>1324</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>31</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

