<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <link href="http://arxiv.org/api/query?search_query%3Dall%3Abiogeography%20AND%20all%3Amachine%20AND%20all%3Alearning%26id_list%3D%26start%3D0%26max_results%3D100" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <title type="html">ArXiv Query: search_query=all:biogeography AND all:machine AND all:learning&amp;id_list=&amp;start=0&amp;max_results=100</title>
  <id>http://arxiv.org/api/5CGtZ8BSa3SOZdduJHG8Avrho/0</id>
  <updated>2019-07-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <opensearch:totalResults xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/">2</opensearch:totalResults>
  <opensearch:startIndex xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/">0</opensearch:startIndex>
  <opensearch:itemsPerPage xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/">100</opensearch:itemsPerPage>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/0912.1009v1</id>
    <updated>2009-12-05T12:54:24Z</updated>
    <published>2009-12-05T12:54:24Z</published>
    <title>Biogeography based Satellite Image Classification</title>
    <summary>  Biogeography is the study of the geographical distribution of biological
organisms. The mindset of the engineer is that we can learn from nature.
Biogeography Based Optimization is a burgeoning nature inspired technique to
find the optimal solution of the problem. Satellite image classification is an
important task because it is the only way we can know about the land cover map
of inaccessible areas. Though satellite images have been classified in past by
using various techniques, the researchers are always finding alternative
strategies for satellite image classification so that they may be prepared to
select the most appropriate technique for the feature extraction task in hand.
This paper is focused on classification of the satellite image of a particular
land cover using the theory of Biogeography based Optimization. The original
BBO algorithm does not have the inbuilt property of clustering which is
required during image classification. Hence modifications have been proposed to
the original algorithm and the modified algorithm is used to classify the
satellite image of a given region. The results indicate that highly accurate
land cover features can be extracted effectively when the proposed algorithm is
used.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>V. K. Panchal</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Parminder Singh</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Navdeep Kaur</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Harish Kundra</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">6 pages IEEE format, International Journal of Computer Science and
  Information Security, IJCSIS November 2009, ISSN 1947 5500,
  http://sites.google.com/site/ijcsis/</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">International Journal of Computer Science and Information
  Security, IJCSIS, Vol. 6, No. 2, pp. 269-274, November 2009, USA</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0912.1009v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/0912.1009v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="cs.CV" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.CV" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.LG" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1207.3285v1</id>
    <updated>2012-07-12T19:00:46Z</updated>
    <published>2012-07-12T19:00:46Z</published>
    <title>Biogeography-Based Informative Gene Selection and Cancer Classification
  Using SVM and Random Forests</title>
    <summary>  Microarray cancer gene expression data comprise of very high dimensions.
Reducing the dimensions helps in improving the overall analysis and
classification performance. We propose two hybrid techniques, Biogeography -
based Optimization - Random Forests (BBO - RF) and BBO - SVM (Support Vector
Machines) with gene ranking as a heuristic, for microarray gene expression
analysis. This heuristic is obtained from information gain filter ranking
procedure. The BBO algorithm generates a population of candidate subset of
genes, as part of an ecosystem of habitats, and employs the migration and
mutation processes across multiple generations of the population to improve the
classification accuracy. The fitness of each gene subset is assessed by the
classifiers - SVM and Random Forests. The performances of these hybrid
techniques are evaluated on three cancer gene expression datasets retrieved
from the Kent Ridge Biomedical datasets collection and the libSVM data
repository. Our results demonstrate that genes selected by the proposed
techniques yield classification accuracies comparable to previously reported
algorithms.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Sarvesh Nikumbh</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Shameek Ghosh</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Valadi Jayaraman</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1109/CEC.2012.6256127</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1109/CEC.2012.6256127" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">6 pages; Author's copy; Presented at the IEEE World Congress on
  Computational Intelligence (at IEEE Congress on Evolutionary Computation),
  Brisbane, Australia, June 2012</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1207.3285v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1207.3285v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="cs.NE" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.NE" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="stat.ML" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
