<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <link href="http://arxiv.org/api/query?search_query%3Dall%3Ageology%20AND%20all%3Amachine%20AND%20all%3Alearning%26id_list%3D%26start%3D0%26max_results%3D100" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <title type="html">ArXiv Query: search_query=all:geology AND all:machine AND all:learning&amp;id_list=&amp;start=0&amp;max_results=100</title>
  <id>http://arxiv.org/api/JE2hKeHG1kz4AG3UnpBfRa+ftPE</id>
  <updated>2019-07-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <opensearch:totalResults xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/">14</opensearch:totalResults>
  <opensearch:startIndex xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/">0</opensearch:startIndex>
  <opensearch:itemsPerPage xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/">100</opensearch:itemsPerPage>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1809.06688v1</id>
    <updated>2018-09-07T05:14:37Z</updated>
    <published>2018-09-07T05:14:37Z</published>
    <title>Geology prediction based on operation data of TBM: comparison between
  deep neural network and statistical learning methods</title>
    <summary>  Tunnel boring machine (TBM) is a complex engineering system widely used for
tunnel construction. In view of the complicated construction environments, it
is necessary to predict geology conditions prior to excavation. In recent
years, massive operation data of TBM has been recorded, and mining these data
can provide important references and useful information for designers and
operators of TBM. In this work, a geology prediction approach is proposed based
on deep neural network and operation data. It can provide relatively accurate
geology prediction results ahead of the tunnel face compared with the other
prediction models based on statistical learning methods. The application case
study on a tunnel in China shows that the proposed approach can accurately
estimate the geological conditions prior to excavation, especially for the
short range ahead of training data. This work can be regarded as a good
complement to the geophysical prospecting approach during the construction of
tunnels, and also highlights the applicability and potential of deep neural
networks for other data mining tasks of TBMs.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Maolin Shi</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Xueguan Song</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Wei Sun</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">26 pages, 7 figures</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1809.06688v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1809.06688v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.LG" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1802.03065v3</id>
    <updated>2018-07-05T17:56:39Z</updated>
    <published>2018-02-08T22:41:22Z</published>
    <title>Generating Realistic Geology Conditioned on Physical Measurements with
  Generative Adversarial Networks</title>
    <summary>  An important problem in geostatistics is to build models of the subsurface of
the Earth given physical measurements at sparse spatial locations. Typically,
this is done using spatial interpolation methods or by reproducing patterns
from a reference image. However, these algorithms fail to produce realistic
patterns and do not exhibit the wide range of uncertainty inherent in the
prediction of geology. In this paper, we show how semantic inpainting with
Generative Adversarial Networks can be used to generate varied realizations of
geology which honor physical measurements while matching the expected
geological patterns. In contrast to other algorithms, our method scales well
with the number of data points and mimics a distribution of patterns as opposed
to a single pattern or image. The generated conditional samples are state of
the art.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Emilien Dupont</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Tuanfeng Zhang</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Peter Tilke</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Lin Liang</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>William Bailey</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Added ICML workshop info, more specific training details and more
  details on how images are chosen</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1802.03065v3" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1802.03065v3" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="stat.ML" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="stat.ML" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.comp-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.03677v2</id>
    <updated>2019-04-09T08:41:26Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-07T16:04:56Z</published>
    <title>Parametrization of stochastic inputs using generative adversarial
  networks with application in geology</title>
    <summary>  We investigate artificial neural networks as a parametrization tool for
stochastic inputs in numerical simulations. We address parametrization from the
point of view of emulating the data generating process, instead of explicitly
constructing a parametric form to preserve predefined statistics of the data.
This is done by training a neural network to generate samples from the data
distribution using a recent deep learning technique called generative
adversarial networks. By emulating the data generating process, the relevant
statistics of the data are replicated. The method is assessed in subsurface
flow problems, where effective parametrization of underground properties such
as permeability is important due to the high dimensionality and presence of
high spatial correlations. We experiment with realizations of binary
channelized subsurface permeability and perform uncertainty quantification and
parameter estimation. Results show that the parametrization using generative
adversarial networks is very effective in preserving visual realism as well as
high order statistics of the flow responses, while achieving a dimensionality
reduction of two orders of magnitude.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Shing Chan</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ahmed H. Elsheikh</name>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.03677v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1904.03677v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="cs.LG" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.LG" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.comp-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="stat.ML" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.07659v2</id>
    <updated>2019-04-10T07:09:35Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-12T19:04:58Z</published>
    <title>A Machine Learning Benchmark for Facies Classification</title>
    <summary>  The recent interest in using deep learning for seismic interpretation tasks,
such as facies classification, has been facing a significant obstacle, namely
the absence of large publicly available annotated datasets for training and
testing models. As a result, researchers have often resorted to annotating
their own training and testing data. However, different researchers may
annotate different classes, or use different train and test splits. In
addition, it is common for papers that apply machine learning for facies
classification to not contain quantitative results, and rather rely solely on
visual inspection of the results. All of these practices have lead to
subjective results and have greatly hindered the ability to compare different
machine learning models against each other and understand the advantages and
disadvantages of each approach.
  To address these issues, we open-source a fully-annotated 3D geological model
of the Netherlands F3 Block. This model is based on the study of the 3D seismic
data in addition to 26 well logs, and is grounded on the careful study of the
geology of the region. Furthermore, we propose two baseline models for facies
classification based on a deconvolution network architecture and make their
codes publicly available. Finally, we propose a scheme for evaluating different
models on this dataset, and we share the results of our baseline models. In
addition to making the dataset and the code publicly available, this work helps
advance research in this area by creating an objective benchmark for comparing
the results of different machine learning approaches for facies classification.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Yazeed Alaudah</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Patrycja Michalowicz</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Motaz Alfarraj</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ghassan AlRegib</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Submitted to the SEG Interpretation journal</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.07659v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.07659v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="eess.IV" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="eess.IV" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.CV" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1809.07748v2</id>
    <updated>2018-09-21T09:31:45Z</updated>
    <published>2018-09-20T17:33:20Z</published>
    <title>Exemplar-based synthesis of geology using kernel discrepancies and
  generative neural networks</title>
    <summary>  We propose a framework for synthesis of geological images based on an
exemplar image. We synthesize new realizations such that the discrepancy in the
patch distribution between the realizations and the exemplar image is
minimized. Such discrepancy is quantified using a kernel method for two-sample
test called maximum mean discrepancy. To enable fast synthesis, we train a
generative neural network in an offline phase to sample realizations
efficiently during deployment, while also providing a parametrization of the
synthesis process. We assess the framework on a classical binary image
representing channelized subsurface reservoirs, finding that the method
reproduces the visual patterns and spatial statistics (image histogram and
two-point probability functions) of the exemplar image.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Shing Chan</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ahmed H. Elsheikh</name>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1809.07748v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1809.07748v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="stat.ML" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="stat.ML" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.CV" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.LG" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="stat.AP" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.11834v2</id>
    <updated>2019-05-03T15:11:32Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-26T13:12:40Z</published>
    <title>DeepFreak: Learning Crystallography Diffraction Patterns with Automated
  Machine Learning</title>
    <summary>  Serial crystallography is the field of science that studies the structure and
properties of crystals via diffraction patterns. In this paper, we introduce a
new serial crystallography dataset comprised of real and synthetic images; the
synthetic images are generated through the use of a simulator that is both
scalable and accurate. The resulting dataset is called DiffraNet, and it is
composed of 25,457 512x512 grayscale labeled images. We explore several
computer vision approaches for classification on DiffraNet such as standard
feature extraction algorithms associated with Random Forests and Support Vector
Machines but also an end-to-end CNN topology dubbed DeepFreak tailored to work
on this new dataset. All implementations are publicly available and have been
fine-tuned using off-the-shelf AutoML optimization tools for a fair comparison.
Our best model achieves 98.5% accuracy on synthetic images and 94.51% accuracy
on real images. We believe that the DiffraNet dataset and its classification
methods will have in the long term a positive impact in accelerating
discoveries in many disciplines, including chemistry, geology, biology,
materials science, metallurgy, and physics.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Artur Souza</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Leonardo B. Oliveira</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sabine Hollatz</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Matt Feldman</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Kunle Olukotun</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>James M. Holton</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Aina E. Cohen</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Luigi Nardi</name>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.11834v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1904.11834v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="cs.LG" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.LG" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.CV" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="stat.ML" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1812.08655v1</id>
    <updated>2018-12-12T03:56:20Z</updated>
    <published>2018-12-12T03:56:20Z</published>
    <title>Surrogate-assisted Bayesian inversion for landscape and basin evolution
  models</title>
    <summary>  The complex and computationally expensive features of the forward landscape
and sedimentary basin evolution models pose a major challenge in the
development of efficient inference and optimization methods. Bayesian inference
provides a methodology for estimation and uncertainty quantification of free
model parameters. In our previous work, parallel tempering Bayeslands was
developed as a framework for parameter estimation and uncertainty
quantification for the landscape and basin evolution modelling software
Badlands. Parallel tempering Bayeslands features high-performance computing
with dozens of processing cores running in parallel to enhance computational
efficiency. Although parallel computing is used, the procedure remains
computationally challenging since thousands of samples need to be drawn and
evaluated. In large-scale landscape and basin evolution problems, a single
model evaluation can take from several minutes to hours, and in certain cases,
even days. Surrogate-assisted optimization has been with successfully applied
to a number of engineering problems. This motivates its use in optimisation and
inference methods suited for complex models in geology and geophysics.
Surrogates can speed up parallel tempering Bayeslands by developing
computationally inexpensive surrogates to mimic expensive models. In this
paper, we present an application of surrogate-assisted parallel tempering where
that surrogate mimics a landscape evolution model including erosion, sediment
transport and deposition, by estimating the likelihood function that is given
by the model. We employ a machine learning model as a surrogate that learns
from the samples generated by the parallel tempering algorithm. The results
show that the methodology is effective in lowering the overall computational
cost significantly while retaining the quality of solutions.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Rohitash Chandra</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Danial Azam</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Arpit Kapoor</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>R. Dietmar Müller</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Under review. arXiv admin note: text overlap with arXiv:1811.08687</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1812.08655v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1812.08655v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="stat.ML" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="stat.ML" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.DC" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.LG" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.NE" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1905.11079v2</id>
    <updated>2019-06-11T15:06:32Z</updated>
    <published>2019-05-27T09:31:12Z</published>
    <title>Learning to Discretize: Solving 1D Scalar Conservation Laws via Deep
  Reinforcement Learning</title>
    <summary>  Conservation laws are considered to be fundamental laws of nature. It has
broad application in many fields including physics, chemistry, biology,
geology, and engineering. Solving the differential equations associated with
conservation laws is a major branch in computational mathematics. Recent
success of machine learning, especially deep learning, in areas such as
computer vision and natural language processing, has attracted a lot of
attention from the community of computational mathematics and inspired many
intriguing works in combining machine learning with traditional methods. In
this paper, we are the first to explore the possibility and benefit of solving
nonlinear conservation laws using deep reinforcement learning. As a proof of
concept, we focus on 1-dimensional scalar conservation laws. We deploy the
machinery of deep reinforcement learning to train a policy network that can
decide on how the numerical solutions should be approximated in a sequential
and spatial-temporal adaptive manner. We will show that the problem of solving
conservation laws can be naturally viewed as a sequential decision making
process and the numerical schemes learned in such a way can easily enforce
long-term accuracy. Furthermore, the learned policy network can determine a
good local discrete approximation based on the current state of the solution,
which essentially makes the proposed method a meta-learning approach. In other
words, the proposed method is capable of learning how to discretize for a given
situation mimicking human experts. Finally, we will provide details on how the
policy network is trained, how well it performs compared with some
state-of-the-art numerical solvers such as WENO schemes, and how well it
generalizes.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Yufei Wang</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ziju Shen</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Zichao Long</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Bin Dong</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">submitted to NeurIPS 2019</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1905.11079v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1905.11079v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="cs.LG" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.LG" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.NA" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="math.NA" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.comp-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1806.05114v2</id>
    <updated>2019-01-28T22:39:04Z</updated>
    <published>2018-06-12T16:37:53Z</published>
    <title>Earthquake Detection in 1-D Time Series Data with Feature Selection and
  Dictionary Learning</title>
    <summary>  Earthquakes can be detected by matching spatial patterns or phase properties
from 1-D seismic waves. Current earthquake detection methods, such as waveform
correlation and template matching, have difficulty detecting anomalous
earthquakes that are not similar to other earthquakes. In recent years,
machine-learning techniques for earthquake detection have been emerging as a
new active research direction. In this paper, we develop a novel earthquake
detection method based on dictionary learning. Our detection method first
generates rich features via signal processing and statistical methods and
further employs feature selection techniques to choose features that carry the
most significant information. Based on these selected features, we build a
dictionary for classifying earthquake events from non-earthquake events. To
evaluate the performance of our dictionary-based detection methods, we test our
method on a labquake dataset from Penn State University, which contains
3,357,566 time series data points with a 400 MHz sampling rate. 1,000
earthquake events are manually labeled in total, and the length of these
earthquake events varies from 74 to 7151 data points. Through comparison to
other detection methods, we show that our feature selection and dictionary
learning incorporated earthquake detection method achieves an 80.1% prediction
accuracy and outperforms the baseline methods in earthquake detection,
including Template Matching (TM) and Support Vector Machine (SVM).
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Zheng Zhou</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Youzuo Lin</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Zhongping Zhang</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Yue Wu</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Johnson</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Workshop on Data Mining for Geophysics and Geology, SIAM
  International Conference on Data Mining 2018</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1806.05114v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1806.05114v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1807.05207v2</id>
    <updated>2019-07-15T15:54:11Z</updated>
    <published>2018-07-13T17:46:00Z</published>
    <title>Parametric generation of conditional geological realizations using
  generative neural networks</title>
    <summary>  Deep learning techniques are increasingly being considered for geological
applications where -- much like in computer vision -- the challenges are
characterized by high-dimensional spatial data dominated by multipoint
statistics. In particular, a novel technique called generative adversarial
networks has been recently studied for geological parametrization and
synthesis, obtaining very impressive results that are at least qualitatively
competitive with previous methods. The method obtains a neural network
parametrization of the geology -- so-called a generator -- that is capable of
reproducing very complex geological patterns with dimensionality reduction of
several orders of magnitude. Subsequent works have addressed the conditioning
task, i.e. using the generator to generate realizations honoring spatial
observations (hard data). The current approaches, however, do not provide a
parametrization of the conditional generation process. In this work, we propose
a method to obtain a parametrization for direct generation of conditional
realizations. The main idea is to simply extend the existing generator network
by stacking a second inference network that learns to perform the conditioning.
This inference network is a neural network trained to sample a posterior
distribution derived using a Bayesian formulation of the conditioning task. The
resulting extended neural network thus provides the conditional
parametrization. Our method is assessed on a benchmark image of binary
channelized subsurface, obtaining very promising results for a wide variety of
conditioning configurations.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Shing Chan</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ahmed H. Elsheikh</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1007/s10596-019-09850-7</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10596-019-09850-7" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Computational Geosciences (2019)</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1807.05207v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1807.05207v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="stat.ML" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="stat.ML" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.LG" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.comp-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1708.01810v2</id>
    <updated>2019-04-09T08:01:07Z</updated>
    <published>2017-08-05T19:07:06Z</published>
    <title>Parametrization and generation of geological models with generative
  adversarial networks</title>
    <summary>  One of the main challenges in the parametrization of geological models is the
ability to capture complex geological structures often observed in the
subsurface. In recent years, generative adversarial networks (GAN) were
proposed as an efficient method for the generation and parametrization of
complex data, showing state-of-the-art performances in challenging computer
vision tasks such as reproducing natural images (handwritten digits, human
faces, etc.). In this work, we study the application of Wasserstein GAN for the
parametrization of geological models. The effectiveness of the method is
assessed for uncertainty propagation tasks using several test cases involving
different permeability patterns and subsurface flow problems. Results show that
GANs are able to generate samples that preserve the multipoint statistical
features of the geological models both visually and quantitatively. The
generated samples reproduce both the geological structures and the flow
statistics of the reference geology.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Shing Chan</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ahmed H. Elsheikh</name>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1708.01810v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1708.01810v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="stat.ML" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="stat.ML" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.comp-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.data-an" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1805.05090v1</id>
    <updated>2018-05-14T09:57:25Z</updated>
    <published>2018-05-14T09:57:25Z</published>
    <title>Hyperspectral Data Analysis in R: the hsdar Package</title>
    <summary>  Hyperspectral remote sensing is a promising tool for a variety of
applications including ecology, geology, analytical chemistry and medical
research. This article presents the new \hsdar package for R statistical
software, which performs a variety of analysis steps taken during a typical
hyperspectral remote sensing approach. The package introduces a new class for
efficiently storing large hyperspectral datasets such as hyperspectral cubes
within R. The package includes several important hyperspectral analysis tools
such as continuum removal, normalized ratio indices and integrates two widely
used radiation transfer models. In addition, the package provides methods to
directly use the functionality of the caret package for machine learning tasks.
Two case studies demonstrate the package's range of functionality: First, plant
leaf chlorophyll content is estimated and second, cancer in the human larynx is
detected from hyperspectral data.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Lukas W. Lehnert</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Hanna Meyer</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Wolfgang A. Obermeier</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Brenner Silva</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Bianca Regeling</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jörg Bendix</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.18637/jss.v089.i12</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.18637/jss.v089.i12" rel="related"/>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1805.05090v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1805.05090v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="stat.OT" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="stat.OT" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1705.09269v1</id>
    <updated>2017-05-25T17:25:04Z</updated>
    <published>2017-05-25T17:25:04Z</published>
    <title>Geometric Methods for Robust Data Analysis in High Dimension</title>
    <summary>  Machine learning and data analysis now finds both scientific and industrial
application in biology, chemistry, geology, medicine, and physics. These
applications rely on large quantities of data gathered from automated sensors
and user input. Furthermore, the dimensionality of many datasets is extreme:
more details are being gathered about single user interactions or sensor
readings. All of these applications encounter problems with a common theme: use
observed data to make inferences about the world. Our work obtains the first
provably efficient algorithms for Independent Component Analysis (ICA) in the
presence of heavy-tailed data. The main tool in this result is the centroid
body (a well-known topic in convex geometry), along with optimization and
random walks for sampling from a convex body. This is the first algorithmic use
of the centroid body and it is of independent theoretical interest, since it
effectively replaces the estimation of covariance from samples, and is more
generally accessible.
  This reduction relies on a non-linear transformation of samples from such an
intersection of halfspaces (i.e. a simplex) to samples which are approximately
from a linearly transformed product distribution. Through this transformation
of samples, which can be done efficiently, one can then use an ICA algorithm to
recover the vertices of the intersection of halfspaces.
  Finally, we again use ICA as an algorithmic primitive to construct an
efficient solution to the widely-studied problem of learning the parameters of
a Gaussian mixture model. Our algorithm again transforms samples from a
Gaussian mixture model into samples which fit into the ICA model and, when
processed by an ICA algorithm, result in recovery of the mixture parameters.
Our algorithm is effective even when the number of Gaussians in the mixture
grows polynomially with the ambient dimension
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Joseph Anderson</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">180 Pages, 7 Figures, PhD thesis, Ohio State (2017)</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1705.09269v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1705.09269v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="cs.LG" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.LG" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1709.02885v1</id>
    <updated>2017-09-09T00:30:42Z</updated>
    <published>2017-09-09T00:30:42Z</published>
    <title>Network of Nano-Landers for In-Situ Characterization of Asteroid Impact
  Studies</title>
    <summary>  Exploration of asteroids and comets can give insight into the origins of the
solar system and can be instrumental in planetary defence and in-situ resource
utilization (ISRU). Asteroids, due to their low gravity are a challenging
target for surface exploration. Current missions envision performing
touch-and-go operations over an asteroid surface. In this work, we analyse the
feasibility of sending scores of nano-landers, each 1 kg in mass and volume of
1U, or 1000 cm3. These landers would hop, roll and fly over the asteroid
surface. The landers would include science instruments such as stereo cameras,
hand-lens imagers and spectrometers to characterize rock composition. A network
of nano-landers situated on the surface of an asteroid can provide unique and
very detailed measurements of a spacecraft impacting onto an asteroid surface.
A full-scale, artificial impact experiment onto an asteroid can help
characterize its composition and geology and help in the development of
asteroid deflection techniques intended for planetary defence. Scores of
nano-landers could provide multiple complementary views of the impact,
resultant seismic activity and trajectory of the ejecta. The nano-landers can
analyse the pristine, unearthed regolith shielded from effects of UV and cosmic
rays and that may be millions of years old. Our approach to formulating this
mission concepts utilizes automated machine learning techniques in the planning
and design of space systems. We use a form of Darwinian selection to select and
identify suitable number of nano-landers, the on-board instruments and control
system to explore and navigate the asteroid environment. Scenarios are
generated in simulation and evaluated against quantifiable mission goals such
as area explored on the asteroid and amount of data recorded from the impact
event.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Himangshu Kalita</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Erik Asphaug</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Stephen Schwartz</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jekanthan Thangavelautham</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">11 pages, 19 figures appearing in the International Astronautical
  Congress 2017, Adelaide, Australia</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1709.02885v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1709.02885v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="cs.RO" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.RO" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
